And here we are in Minecraft,
on a deserted island.
우리는 지금 마인크래프트에서
버려진 외딴 섬에 와 있습니다.
There's a few things we need to do
in order to survive the night.
여기서 밤을 살아남기 위해서는
몇가지 해야 하는 일들이 있습니다.
'Cause what's going to happen is that sun
is going to rise, and then it's going to fall.
왜냐하면 저기 보이는 저 태양이
점점 떠올랐다가 집니다.
And when it falls,
that's when darkness descends on us,
그리고 해가 지면,
그때 어둠이 우리를 엄습해 옵니다.
and that's when the bad things come out of the dark
at night and hunt me down and try to eat me.
그리고 그때가 어둠속에서 적들이 우리를
사냥해 잡아먹으려고 나타나는 때 입니다.
When did I first hear about Minecraft?
저는 마인크래프트에 대해서 언제 처음 들어봤냐고요?
Where was I when JFK was assassinated,
basically, kind of thing?
무슨 케네디 대통령이 암살 당했을 때
어디에 있었는지와 같은 그런 질문인가요?
My awareness of Minecraft
did not come from a magazine cover.
제가 마인크래프트에 대해서 처음
알게 된 것은 잡지를 통해서는 아니었습니다.
It's like you hear it a couple times in the hallway,
and it's like, "What? What was that?"
그냥 지나치던 사람들을 통해서 몇번 들어보고
"응? 그게 뭔가요?" 하는 식으로 물어봐서 알게 되었죠.
It accelerated so quickly, obviously,
that it's hard to recall that starting point,
너무 갑자기 유명해져서 딱히 어느 시점이
이 모든 것의 시작이라고 말하기가 어렵습니다.
because after that, obviously,
it caught like wild fire.
유명세를 조금 타기 시작하더니
들불처럼 펴지기 시작했으니까요.
It's a very unique
success story, really.
참 보기 드문 성공담 입니다.
정말로요.
In the past, you know,
five to ten years,
지난 5~10년 동안,
여러분들도 아시다시피
there's been some brilliant moments in gaming,
and Minecraft is definitely one of them.
게임 산업에서는 획기적인 일들이 있었습니다.
마인크래프트의 등장도 당연히 하나입니다.
Happy New Year.
새해 복 많이 받으세요.
Everything's, sort of,
happening at once.
정말로 많은 일들이
동시다발적으로 일어나고 있습니다.
You have this very clear, like,
starting point.
하지만 어쨌든 새로운
시작점이라고도 할 수 있을것 같은데요.
Yeah, I know, I took like a week off
during the Christmas and New Year's,
예 그렇습니다. 그래서 크리스마스와 새해 첫날을
이용해 1주일 정도 휴식을 취했습니다.
and it was just, like,
almost emotional, like, kind of weird, like,
감회가 새로웠고, 기분도 약간 묘했습니다.
그러니까 이런 생각이 들더군요.
"Oh, okay, all this has happened
and I haven't really relaxed until now."
"아, 그래, 그동안 많은 일이 있었고
지금까지 한순간도 제대로 쉬어보지 못했군"
And then when I came back, the office felt really good;
and just; the first thing I did was work, like, 12 hours.
그러고는 사무실에 돌아왔을때 너무 좋았는데,
가장 먼저 한 일이 12시간 일하는 것이었습니다.
Let's just start with growing up in Sweden;
what area of the country were you originally from?
그럼 스웨덴에서 성장한 이야기 부터 시작해 봅시다.
스웨덴의 어느지방에서 성장 했나요?
Well, the first seven years of my life I lived
out in the countryside in a place called Edsybn.
제 생의 첫 7년은 지방에 위치한
Edsybn이라는 곳에서 살았습니다.
It's like, a bit north in the country;
very snowy winters.
그러니까 약간 북쪽 지방이고요
겨울에 눈이 참 많이 내리는 곳이었습니다.
At least, that's how I remember;
and really warm summers.
적어도 전 그렇게 기억하고 있습니다.
그리고 여름은 따뜻했습니다.
We went out, walked around in the woods,
just getting lost, basically.
우리는 밖에 나가서 숲속에서 쉽게 말해
많이 싸돌아다녔습니다.
And I did that and programming,
basically my two hobbies
그렇게 놀면서 프로그래밍을 했습니다.
그 두 가지가 제 취미였습니다.
No, I've been programming
since I was eight, or something.
아니, 저는 한 8살이 되었을 때 쯤에
프로그래밍을 시작했군요.
I kinda always knew that I wanted to make games,
and I said so in school to my, like...
저는 제가 게임을 만들고 싶다는 것을 늘 알고 있었기에
학교에서도 그렇게 말했습니다. 그랬더니...
...Career Counselor thing, and she said,
"Oh, well, that's probably not gonna happen."
진로 상담사라고 해야 하나? 그 분께서
"아, 그래? 하지만 그런일은 없을것 같구나" 라고 말씀하셨죠.
Yeah.
네, 그러셨답니다.
That's what he likes to do, you know;
but he always made games, you know;
그것이 그 사람이 좋아하는 일이에요.
그 사람은 언제나 게임을 만들어 왔죠.
I always found it interesting
to try out his games.
저는 그 사람이 만든 게임을 시도해
보는 것에 대해서 항상 흥미를 느껴요.
And I was like,
"Yeah, you're a genius!"
시도해 보고는 늘 이렇게 말합니다
"야호~ 너는 천재야!"
I like hanging out at his place, and he would like,
"do-do-do-do-do," you know,
저는 그 사람 집에서 죽치는것을 좋아해요.
그 사람이 컴퓨터로 "두-두-두-두-두" 이렇게
be on the computer,
and I like hearing that sound.
컴퓨터로 작업하고 있으면,
저는 그 소리를 듣는 것이 좋아요.
So, but, it's very much like an artist,
because he has so much integrity in his work.
그 사람은 마치 예술인과 같아요.
자기의 창작물에 자신의 혼을 불어 넣거든요.
Markus and I, we've been friends for the four
and a half years that we worked together at King.<
마커스와 저는 4년반 가까이
King에서 같이 일하면서 친구로 지냈습니다.
And we became close, and we had a lot of fun,
and then of course he had the success,
그러면서 친해졌고, 같이 많이 재미있었습니다.
하지만 이제 그는 큰 성공을 거두게 되었죠.
'cause he left King to start--
basically he wanted to do games in his free time.
그것은 그가 King을 떠났기 때문에 가능했습니다.
그는 항상 한가한 시간에 게임을 만들기를 원했습니다.
And while we were working with King,
we were allowed to make games in our spare time,
King에서 우리가 같이 근무할 때도 물론
우리는 남는 시간에 게임을 만들 수는 있었습니다.
but we couldn't do it as a business;
and he wanted to try that.
하지만 그것을 사업으로 이어갈 수는 없었죠.
하지만 그는 사업을 할 수 있기를 바랬습니다.
I was sad, of course, that he left,
because we had a great time at King.
저는 그가 일을 그만둔다는 것이 당연히 슬펐습니다.
하지만 우리는 King에서 좋은 추억을 만들었고,
You know, I lost my best buddy,
my best working buddy;
비록 제 가장 친한 동료를,
일을 하는데 있어서 가장 좋은 동지를 잃었지만
but I wasn't worried for him,
and we stayed in touch regardless.
그의 앞날에 대해 크게 우려한 적은 없었습니다.
그리고 같이 일할 수 없게 되었어도 계속 연락을 하고 지냈죠.
So I left to make my own games, and the first thing
I was gonna do was just gonna be, like a,
저는 제 자신만의 게임을 만들기 위해 떠났습니다.
그리고 제가 가장 처음 한 일은, 그러니까...
six to twelve month project;
and it kinda turned into what Minecraft is now, fairly soon.
6개월에서 1년 정도의 프로젝트를 시작하는 것이었는데,
그게 생각보다 빠르게 지금의 마인크래프트와 유사하게 개발 되었습니다.
But in the beginning, it was, I mean; it was so basic,
you can place blocks on other boxes or blocks.
처음에는 뭐라고 해야 할까요? 너무 기초적이라고 해야 할까요?
블록을 옮기고 블록 위에 블록을 올려 놓을 수 있는 정도였습니다.
So yeah, I got to be there
and look at it from the start.
저는 그 순간 거기에 있었습니다.
처음부터 어떻게 개발 되었는지 볼 수 있었죠.
Of course in the beginning, the world was more limited;
you had the edges; you would fall off.
물론 초창기에는 마인크래프트의 세상은 제한적이어서,
세상 끝에 있는 낭떠러지에 떨어질 수도 있었습니다.
I don't think anybody could predict
the success of Minecraft from looking at it back then.
저는 어느 누구도 그 당시의 마인크래프틀 보고
성공을 예상하지는 못했을 것이라고 생각합니다.
I really liked the game from the start;
it's like a digital Lego, you know?
저는 처음부터 게임이 매우 마음에 들었습니다.
마치 디지털 레고를 하는것 같았어요. 무슨 말인지 아시겠어요?
You have blocks, you can build things,
and people are like, "Oh, this isn't so fun."
블록들이 당신에게 주어지고, 그것들로 무엇인가 만들 수 있다고 말하면,
사람들은 "어? 그거 별로 재미 없을것 같아"라고 말합니다.
You know, it's hard to explain;
I usually say, "Okay,
알고보면 참 설명하기 힘들어요.
저는 보통 이렇게 말해요. "그래,
but it's about surviving, as well;
you have monsters you have to fight,
하지만 게임 속에서 괴물들이 나타나면
싸우기도 하면서 생존해야 한다는 요소도 있어.
you have to build your house
and collect stuff to be able to survive."
그래서 집도 짛어야 하고 살아남을 수 있도록
여러가지 자원도 모아야 한다고."
So it's a bit like being stuck at a desert island, like,
figure out what to do.
그러니까 쉽게 말해 무인도에 갖혀서
무엇을 해야 하는지 찾아내야 하는 것입니다.
Let's go to a place
where everything is made of blocks...
모든 것이 블록으로 만들어진 곳으로
한번 같이 떠나볼까요?
...where the only limit
is your imagination.
당신의 상상력이 허락하는 한계가 당신이
할 수 있는 일의 한계인 그곳
Let's go wherever you wanna go;
climb the tallest mountains,
당신이 가보고 싶은 곳 어디든지 가보고
가장 높은 산을 한번 올라가 봅시다.
venture down
to the darkest caves,
가장 깊고 어두운
동굴도 탐험해 보고,
build anything you want,
day or night, rain or shine;
무엇이든지 만들어 보세요
밤낮 가리지 않고, 날씨 불문하고.
'cause this is the most significant sandbox
you'll ever set foot in.
왜냐하면 이곳은 여러분이 발을 들여 놓을 수 있는
가장 훌륭한 놀이터가 될 것이기 때문입니다.
Yeah, I usually tell people,
"Well, you have to try play it; you won't understand."
네, 그러니까 저는 보통 사람들에게 이렇게 말해요,
"그러니까, 너도 한번 해봐야해. 안 해보면 이해 못할거야."
To be honest, I really didn't understand
the power of the game in the beginning.
솔직히 말해서, 저도 처음에는 이 게임이
가질 수 있는 영향력에 대해 이해할 수 없었습니다.
I think at the point where Markus took me aside
at the office and said, "I really need to focus on this,"
저는 마커스가 어느날 저를 사무실 한쪽으로 불러 세워서
"나는 이 일에 정말 집중해겠어"라고 말하면서
and he told me about the success, and you know,
what kind of numbers he had.
그동안 그가 거둔 성공을 구체적인
숫자들(역주: 사용자, 다운로드 수)을 알려주었을 때
Then I realized that this
is gonna be something big.
그때서야 저는 이것이 정말
대박 치겠다는 것을 깨달았습니다.
At first it was 40 sales for a day,
then it was like, 10,000 sales a day, you know?
초반에는 하루에 40 카피를 팔았고, 어느덧
하루에 만 카피를 파는 날이 왔어요. 믿어지세요?
I don't remember the date,
but when I had a million Swedish Crowns in the account...
정확한 날짜는 기억하지는 못하지만,
제 계좌에 백만 크라운(역주: 스웨덴 화폐단위)이 들어왔을때...
...was, definitely
one of the bigger milestones.
...그것은 정말 우리가 이루어낸
과도기적인 일들 중에 좀 큰 사건이었다고 생각합니다.
And I got a print-out of the receipt,
showed Elin, joking, and jokingly said,
그래서 저는 통장 잔고를 종이에 출력해서,
엘린에게 보여주면서 농담조로 이렇게 말했습니다.
"Well, they say the first million is the most difficult,"
like I didn't expect to make another million.
"아마도 첫 백만 만드는 것이 제일 힘들다고 하지?"
정말로 백만 크라운을 더 벌 수 있으리라 기대는 안했거든요.
I did.
그런데 벌었습니다.
You know, it's been like this process
of constantly being amazed.
그러니까 계속 이런 놀라운 일들이
지속적으로 발생하는 과정을 경험했습니다.
Then like, early this year,
it got a big popularity spike on the site;
그러다가 올해 초에는
갑자기 사이트가 유명세를 탔어요.
but I probably need to start a company here,
'cause I can't keep up with the demand of the game.
그때서야 저는 회사를 차려야할 필요가 있다는 생각을 했습니다.
더이상 게임에 대한 요구사항들을 제때 충족시키지 못하게 되었거든요.
I called Jacob and just told him,
"Just quit your job; we're starting a company."
그래서 저는 Jacob에게 전화를 걸어서 말했습니다
"그냥 지금 하는 일 그만둬, 우리 회사 차릴거야."
With the success of Minecraft,
we get the chance to actually do something like this.
우리는 마인크래프트의 성공을 통해서 사실상
이런 일들을 이룰 수 있는 기회를 얻게 되었습니다.
I'm not gonna turn that down.
저는 그 기회를 져버릴 수 없습니다.
So now we're seven people
and we have an office.
그래서 지금 우리는 7명이 되었고
사무실도 갖게 되었습니다.
It's a new year,
and it's finally beta.
새해가 시작 되었고
드디어 베타가 나왔습니다.
It's a very unique
success story, really.
참 보기 드문 성공담 입니다.
정말로요.
The problem is is that Minecraft
never had a publicity department, a PR department.
참 이해하기 힘든 부분은 마인크래프트가
홍보 부서나 PR 담당 부서가 한번도 존재 하지 않았다는 것입니다.
They just did it all virally
and through word of mouth.
바이러스가 퍼지듯이
입소문을 타고 모든것이 이루어졌죠.
And, you know,
it sold three million copies off that.
그래서 아십니까? 그 방법만으로만
3백만 카피나 팔았습니다.
If you are not familiar with this game,
this game is amazing.
만약 당신이 이 게임이 생소하다면
이 게임은 굉장합니다.
I love this game so much,
I've been watching a ton of videos on YouTube.
저는 이 게임을 매우 좋아해서 유튜브를
통해서 관련 영상을 수도 없이 봤습니다.
I've been playing
a ton of this game.
그리고 이 게임을
수도 없이 했습니다.
There's something really magical about
when it first came out, and nobody knew much about it,
뭔가 마력 같은 것이, 처음 나왔을때
아무도 이 게임에 대해서 잘 알지 못했는데
and we're all learning
at the same time.
어느새 모두 다 같이
배우고 있었습니다.
Have you seen this crazy thing?
이 요상한 게임을 봤나요?
Look at this, look what you can do with here;
and people talking about it,
이것 좀 보세요, 여기서 무엇을 할 수 있는지지 보세요!
라며 사람들이 말을 했습니다.
and I could not comprehend
what they were talking about.
그런데 저는 그들이 무엇을 이야기 하는지
도대체 알아들을 수 없었습니다.
I was like, "You did what in this game? This is insane.
I can't imagine it functions like you say it does."
저는 이랬죠, "당신이 이 게임으로 무엇을 했다고?
제 정신으로 이해할 수 없는데? 당신이 말한대로 게임이 된다고?"
Let's talk Minecraft;
you've probably seen it popping up everywhere lately.
우리 마인크래프트에 대해서 말해 봅시다.
아마도 최근에 여기저기서 이 게임에 관한 것을 봤을겁니다.
If you have not played it yet though,
we're about to school you,
아직도 이 게임을 해보지 않았다면,
우리가 입문시켜줄 참입니다.
because it's one of the best
gaming experiences out there right now.
왜냐하면 이 게임이 현재 나와 있는 게임들
가운데 최고의 게이밍 경험을 제공해 주기 때문입니다.
I remember loading it up for the first time,
and nothing; you're just standing there with two hands.
저는 게임을 가장 처음으로 로딩했을 때를 기억하는데,
그냥 아무것도 없었습니다. 내가 그냥 빈손 두개로 서있을 뿐이죠.
And so I hit a tree and wood came out;
and I was like, "Oh no."
그래서 나무를 한번 쳐봤는데, 나무 조각이 나왔는데,
저는 그것을 보고 이랬습니다, "설마..."
Like, I could already see the spiral;
it was like, I hit this tree and wood came out. 그때 이미 어떻게 돌아가는지 빤히 보였습니다
그러니까, 내가 나무를 치면 나무 조각이 나오고.
And then I, you know,
hit the ground and rock comes out.
그리고, 그러니까 땅을 쳐보면
돌맹이 조각이 나오고.
I was like,
"Oh no, this is gonna be bad."
그것을 보고 이랬죠,
"설마... 이거 안좋아 보이는데?"
And then it's that first night
that you spend holed up;
그래서 그 첫날 밤에는 구멍에
숨어 보내게 되죠.
all you can dig out is like,
maybe four squares before it gets dark,
아마 4개의 조각 정도만
해가 지기 전에 파낼 수 있죠.
and you just pile blocks up
as the zombies running around outside.
그 다음에 좀비들이 밖에 나돌아다니는 것을
보고 블록들을 쌓아올리겠죠.
That moment, like,
I won't ever forget that.
그 순간. 그러니까
그 순간은 절대 잊을 수 없습니다.
That is a moment in video gaming
that will always be with me.
비디오 게임을 하는데 있어서 그 순간은
언제나 제 곁에 영원이 있을 것 입니다.
And to me,
that was what sparked my interest in the game.
저에게 있어서 그 순간이
그 게임에 관심을 갖게된 결정적 계기였습니다.
Like, holy cow, this is--
I can do whatever I want here.
어머나 세상에, 그러니까...
나는 여기서 무엇이든지 할 수 있구나!
And so that's the first part of this game;
which is, you know, exploring and collecting resources.
그것이 바로 이 게임의 가장 기본이 되는 부분입니다.
탐험하고 자원을 모으는것 말입니다.
People saw the potential in it,
and if you had the opportunity to play it at a friend's,
사람들은 이 게임이 가지는 잠재력을 봤습니다.
예를 들어 친구의 집에서 이 게임을 해볼 기회가 생긴다거나,
or you saw a video on YouTube, for example,
I think the game pretty much sold itself.
유튜브에서 관련 영상을 봤다면
그 자체로 게임이 톡톡히 홍보 되었다고 생각합니다.
This is my house here, as you can see.
이곳은 여러분께 보이듯이 제 집입니다.
All you do is you put it in the center here, like this,
and then set a fire to it.
이 가운데에다가 이것을 넣기만 하고
불을 붙여 주기만 하면 됩니다.
And not always, but most--
uh-oh.
그리고 항상은 아니지만, 대부분의 경우에...
어엇!?!
Uh, sorry, sorry guys;
this is not supposed to happen.
어, 죄송합니다. 여러분 죄송합니다.
이렇게 되면 안돼는데.
Crap!
Oh, no way!
아, 이럴수가!
Yeah;
you have got to be kidding me.
이런
설마 정말 일어나고 있는 일은 아니겠지?
You know, a lot of people
that saw those videos
아시죠? 관련 영상을 본
많은 사람들이
were instantly in love with the game too,
just by watching someone else play.
즉각적으로 이 게임과 사랑에 빠지게 되었습니다.
그저 다른 사람이 플레이 하는 것을 보는것 만으로도요.
Okay, it is time I go exploring;
where should I go?
자, 제가 탐험을 떠나야할 때가 왔습니다.
어디로 갈까요?
I'm going to climb to the top of this,
and I am going to see what is up there.
저는 저 꼭대기로 올라가야 겠네요,
그리고 저 위에는 무엇이 있는지 봐야겠어요.
I'm joining Stu, and we're in the Minecraft multi-player;
we're exploring the cave here.
저는 스튜와 동참해서 마인크래프트 멀티플레이어를 하면서
이 동굴을 같이 탐험하고 있습니다.
Uh, whoa!
Jesus, that scared the crap out of me!
어, 으악!
세상에, 저것 때문에 놀라 똥쌀뻔 했네!
Oh my God, oh my God,
oh my God!
어머나 세상에, 어머나 세상에
어머나 세상에!
Pull this switch here
and the flood starts.
이 스위치를 잡아당기면
물이 넘치기 시작합니다.
Plop, plop, plop, plop goes the wheat;
plop, plop, plop, plop, plop, plop, plop...
밀이 플롭, 플롭, 플롭, 플롭 거립니다.
플롭, 플롭, 플롭, 플롭, 플롭, 플롭, 플롭...
...moves its way down here till it gets to the very end,
drops into my collection tray.
...여기 끝까지 이동을 시켜서
여기에 떨어뜨려 모아줍니다.
Oh shit, oh shit, oh shit!
Holy shit bro!
아 젠장, 아 젠장, 아 젠장!
젠장 이놈아!
Dude you're so laggy!
이놈아 너 느려터지구나!
I blame it on lag;
damn it!
렉(lag) 때문에 그래
젠장!
You guys get--take cover!
They're firing arrows at us.
얘들아! 나 엄호해줘!
우리한테 화살 쏘고 있잖아.
Ahh, diamond, yes, oh!
Oh my God, there's more; yes!
아아, 다이아몬드! 오 그래!
어머나 세상에, 더 있네? 아싸!
Oh my God,
seven diamond from one.
어머나 세상에,
한번에 7개의 다이아몬드를 캤어!
What's wrong?
Ahh, what's that thing?
뭐가 잘못된거니?
아, 저게 뭐지?
It's a skeleton; I'll kill it for you.
I killed it, yay!
해골이잖아. 내가 엄마를 위해 죽여줄게.
내가 죽였어~ 야호!
-No, no, no, no!
-What's wrong?
-안돼, 안돼, 안돼, 안돼!
-뭐가 잘못 됐니?
-You're jumping into lava!
-What do you mean?
-엄마가 용암으로 뛰어들고 있잖아!
-무슨 말이야?
You're being so bad at Minecraft!
You're in lava.
엄마는 마인크래프트를 너무 못해!
엄마는 지금 용암 속에 있잖아.
-Oh, man!
-You're dying.
-아, 저런!
-엄마는 죽고 있어.
That's horrible.
I died.
그것참 끔찍하네
나 죽었어.
That's okay, Mom.
That's okay.
괜찮아 엄마.
괜찮아.
And you know, this game
had a really special community around it.
아시다시피 이 게임이 있기 까지
정말 특별한 커뮤니티가 있었습니다.
And I think that's a fascinating story that before
the magazines and the TV shows were covering it,
저는 이것이 정말 매력적인 이야기라고 생각하는 것이
잡지나 TV쇼에서 이 게임을 소개하기도 채 전에
there was a whole community
that was loving this game and supporting it,
큰 커뮤니티가 이미 존재 해서
이 게임을 사랑하고 지원해 주고 있었거든요.
and it was really
self-sufficient at that point.
그래서 그 시점에서도 이미
자생이 가능하기에 충분했었죠.
So that could have existed, sort of, in its own little bubble,
but then the world found out about Minecraft.
그래서 그렇게 소수의 사람들 사이에서만 존재할 수도 있었지만
언젠가 세상이 마인크래프트에 대해서 알게 되었습니다.
-All right, what are you?
-Creeper.
-자 그래, 너는 뭐니?
-크리퍼요.
A creeper?
What's a creeper?
크리퍼?
크리퍼가 뭐니?
A creeper is something that blows up
when you touch him!
크리퍼는 누군가 만지게 되면
터져버리는 그런 것이에요!
Is that what you are?
아, 네가 지금 그것이구나?
-Okay, you want to take us in?
-Sure.
-혹시, 안에 구경시켜주실 수 있나요?
-당연하죠.
This is our fancy sign;
here we go, welcome.
이것이 우리의 화려한 간판입니다.
어서 들어가시죠, 환영합니다.
As you can see, it's looking really awful right now;
we're going to remake a lot of things.
보시다시피 지금은 모습이 말이 아닙니다
대부분의 곳은 다시 손을 볼겁니다.
Yeah, I can show you around;
and here we are in the office space.
예, 그럼 더 둘러보시죠.
지금 우리는 사무공간에 있습니다.
We have a PC section
and a Mac section.
PC 구역도 있고요
Mac 구역도 있습니다.
We were thinking about having,
sort of, a Minecraft wallpaper here.
우리는 이쪽 벽에는 마인크래프트를
소재로한 벽지를 붙일 예정입니다.
So this is Jacob;
he's one of the co-founders of Mojang.
자, 이분은 Jacob입니다.
Mojang의 공동 창업자 중에 한 사람이죠.
Over there we have Jeb;
he's a game developer.
저기에는 Jeb이 있네요.
Jeb은 게임 개발자 입니다.
He's sort of the first person
to dive into the Minecraft code.
마인크래프트 코드를 파헤치기 시작한
첫 사람쯤 된다고 할 수 있을것 같습니다.
And so over here we have Daniel Kaplan;
he's the business developer.
그리고 여기는 Daniel Kaplan입니다
그는 사업 기획자(Business Developer)입니다.
Exactly; and here he is, Notch.
I'm sort of showing them around the office,
맞습니다. 여기는 Notch입니다.
지금 이 사람들에게 사무실을 구경 시켜주고 있습니다.
and you're Notch.
-I am Notch.
그리고 당신은 Notch 입니다.
-나는 Notch 입니다.
-He's the reason why we're all here.
-Yes, I am God.
-그가 우리가 모두 여기 있는 이유 입니다.
-그렇습니다, 나는 신 입니다.
-Yes, that's right.
-I am not God.
-네, 맞습니다.
-저는 신이 아닙니다.
-Did I say I'm God on camera?
-Yes, I think you did.
-지금 제가 카메라 앞에서 제가 신이라고 했나요?
-네, 그러신것 같습니다.
I heard that Notch
was starting up a company.
저는 Notch가 회사를
차린다는 소식을 들었습니다.
I played and heard
about Minecraft before, obviously,
저는 그때 이미 마인크래프트를
해봤고 들어본 상태였습니다.
but I didn't know that he wanted
to take it to the next level.
하지만 그가 마인크래프트를 어디까지 어느 수준까지
가지고 가고 싶어하는지 알 수 없었습니다.
So I just sent him an e-mail,
"Hey do you wanna--do you need an artist?"
그래서 무작정 그에게 이메일을 보냈습니다.
"혹시 아티스트가 필요하거나 원하지 않으십니까?"
Got a reply, we met up, and kinda hit it off,
I think, immediately;
답장을 받고, 만나자마자
서로 금방 친해졌습니다.
started joking about prostituting ourselves
to elder women and stuff like that.
여사님들에게 몸을 팔자는 농담도
주고 받기 시작할 정도였습니다. 방
So that's it, really.
And now I'm here.
그것이 다 입니다.
그래서 저는 여기 와 있습니다.
It's also fun to be a part of this so early,
and really be with the core team.
이렇게 이른 시점에서 팀의 일원이 되어서
핵심인력과 함께 할 수 있다는것도 참 즐겁습니다.
I don't know how big we are going to be in the future,
but it's fun to be here from almost the beginning.
우리가 앞으로 얼마나 크게 될지는 저도 잘 모르지만
거의 초창기 부터 함께 할 수 있다는 것 자체가 즐겁습니다.
Well, I started here
two days ago, on Monday.
글쎄요, 저는 이틀전에, 월요일부터
여기서 일하기 시작했습니다.
I went in, signed the contract,
and started working.
들어와서 계약서에 싸인하고
일하기 시작했죠.
-Welcome to Mojang.
-Thank you.
-Mojang에 오신것을 환영합니다.
-감사합니다.
-Great; you've worked here for--
-I've worked here for four hours now, so.
-그래서 여기서 일하신지가...?
-저는 일하기 시작한지 4시간 정도 되었네요.
I've had--got 600 followers on Twitter since Monday;
I had a thread on Reddit discussing me.
저는 월요일 이후로 트위터에 600명의 팔로워가 생겼고,
Reddit에 저에 대해서 논하는 글들이 있었습니다.
It's just an awesome place to be right now,
because it's like...
지금 이 시점에 있기에 딱 좋은 곳입니다.
그러니까 그 이유는
...I catch myself walking down the street,
or just thinking it;
길을 걷거나 하면서 이런 생각을 하는
제 자신을 발견하곤 합니다.
you know, there's not a job out there
that I would rather have, that I would trade in for this.
그러니까, 세상에는 그 어떤 직장도
지금 이 직장과 맞바꿀만한 곳은 없습니다.
I hope he doesn't miss and hit the other guy.
저 사람이 얼음을 잘못쳐서 옆에 있는
사람을 치지 말았으면 좋겠네요.
Punch his pal in the face
and they're all gonna fall and die.
그렇게 되면 친구 얼굴에 주먹을
날리고 둘다 떨어저 죽을거야.
-Oh, you're going to hit it from the other side now?
-Yup, here we go...whoa!
-오, 이제 네가 다른쪽에서 얼음을 깨는건가?
-응, 거의 다 됐나보다. 와!
It feels really good, and it's very interesting,
what's going to happen.
앞으로 벌어질 일들에 대해서
기분이 좋고 상당히 흥미롭습니다.
We're going to have, like a, strategy meeting day thing,
trying to work out what we're actually going to do.
우리는 오늘 사실상 해야 하는 일들이 어떤 것인지
전략회의 같은 것을 오늘 가질 것입니다.
Let's do that again;
can we do that again?
다시 시작합시다.
그래도 될까요?
-Wow.
-That's awfully bouncy.
-와우
-상당히 튀는군요.
We have to decide what actually, like,
the full version of the game is.
우리는 게임이 완성된 형태가
어떤 것인지 사실상 결정해야 합니다.
That's kind of the first step, I guess.
그것이 아마도 우리의 첫 걸음이 되어야 할것 같습니다.
Then the next step is to do that.
그 다음 단계는 그것을 만드는 일입니다.
Minecraft's a very dynamic game,
and it's 'cause it's still in development at the moment.
마인크래프트는 굉장히 역동적인 게임인데,
그것은 아직도 지금 이 순간에 개발되고 있기 때문입니다.
That means that it's continually being updated
with new stuff, and things are changing.
그것은 지속적으로 새로운 것들과 여러 변화로
업데이트 되고 있음을 의미합니다.
Back in like the '80s and the '90s
when you would get a game on PC,
지난 80년대나 90년대에는
PC용 게임을 사게 된다면
or much more often, when you got a game on console,
when you got the game, that was it;
아니면 더욱이 콘솔용 게임을 사게 된다면
게임을 갖게 되는 순간 그것으로 끝이었습니다.
game was done, game wasn't gonna change;
and we've seen that change bit by bit.
게임은 완성 되었고, 게임은 변하지 않았습니다.
그런데 우리는 그런 모습이 조금씩 바뀌는 것을 보았습니다.
And certainly it's happened more on PC
where people can patch and update games,
그 모습은 확실히 사람들이 게임을 패치하고 업데이트
해야 하는 PC에서 더 빈번히 볼 수 있었습니다.
but I think none of that prepared anybody
for how malleable and evolving Minecraft was gonna be;
하지만 제 생각에는 그런 모습들을 통해서도 마인크래프트
만큼의 유연하고 진화하는 것에 준비된 사람은 없었을 것 같습니다.
I mean, to the point
that you could buy the game, ultimately,
그러니까 궁극적으로 게임을 살 수 있는 시점이
more than a year before
it was actually going to be finished,
게임 개발이 사실상 완료되기
1년 전에 구입 해서
and play the game as the creators
were updating the game.
개발자들이 게임을 덥데이트 하는 동안에
게임을 즐길 수 있다는 점에서 말입니다.
And then slowly but surely,
it kind of, you know,
그래서 천천히 하지만 확실하게
그러니까, 이런 방식으로
built attention and anticipation
about where it was gonna go.
앞으로 어떻게 될지에 대한
관심과 기대를 쌓게 해줍니다.
So this is just like, the major headline;
some things we should add now.
그래서 이것들이 우리가 추가해야 할 것들에 대한
대략적인 큰 제목들 입니다.
Yeah, I think it's a bit like--
it's a weird way of making a game.
그래요, 저도 이런 방식으로 게임을
만드는 것은 약간 특이하다고 생각합니다.
You just put it out and kind of
keep working on it as you're making it,
그냥 일단 내다 놓고 계속
작업 하면서 만들어 나가는 것이죠을.
so it's kind of hard to say
is it released, or it's not released?
그래서 릴리스를 했다고 말해야 할지
릴리스가 안됐다고 말해야 할지 애매 합니다.
I try to make sure it's like,
yeah, this is not the game.
그래서 이것이 아직 완성된 게임이 아님을
확인 시켜 주려고 노력합니다.
I'm just working on it and you can play it
while I'm making it.
제가 작업하고는 있지만 그 동안에 여러분이
즐길 수 있는것 뿐이라는 식으로요
Kind of, hopefully.
그런식의 의도로요
Should we go up with the dates, or should we just say this
will be released when it's done?
날짜를 정해놓고 일을 할까요, 아니면
작업이 끝나면 릴리스를 하겠다고 할까요?
Or should we like, try to put up a date
and try to build hype?
아니면 분위기를 이끌어 올리기 위해
날짜를 정해놓는 편이 좋을까요?
I think date and hype;
I vote for that.
날짜를 정해서 분위기를 타는것,
저는 그쪽에 한표
I think there's a difference between this and many other
games in that Minecraft has so many...
저는 이 게임이 다른 게임과 차이가 어떤 면에
있다고 생각하냐면, 마인크래프트는 다양한
...so many users and so many players already;
and as we develop these things,
...사용자층도 있고 이미 많이들 해봤기
때문에 우리가 개발을 진행 하면서
we're gonna--we're not gonna develop in, like,
in a lump and just put them all overnight and say,
우리가 그러니까 개발을, 개발을 하룻밤 사이에
많은 기능을 추가할 수는 없으니까 사람들에게
"Okay, play this game, and now it's done."
It's gonna come, you know--
"자, 이 게임은 완성 되었으니 이제 즐기십시오."
라고 하지는 않을거잖아, 그러니까
every other week or so
it's gonna be small update or a small change,
격주로 조금씩 업데이트 해서
약간의 변화씩만 생길텐데
so can we really live up
to a hype, you know?
그렇게 해서 우리가 과연 사람들의
기대하는 분위기에 부응할 수 있을까요?
This is finally the finished product, and I said,
"Yeah, but it's the same product as last week."
이것은 완성된 제품입니다라고 했는데 제가
"그런데, 이 제품은 지난주에 나온 제품과 똑같아요."라고 말한다면
What do you think of that?
그것에 대해서는 어떻게 생각하십니가?
It is--it's a bit intimidating, yeah.
I felt much more, just confident,
사실 약간 겁이 납니다.
예전에는 자신만만 했었죠.
just going day to day
and just doing things as it went.
하루하루 시간을 보내면서
일이 진행되는 대로 했던때 말입니다.
I don't think that works though,
if you have a company.
하지만 회사를 차린 이상 이제는
그런 방식으로 일하는 것은 통하지 않을것 같습니다.
I'm a bit like--I don't really know
what Minecraft final will be yet,
아직까지는 저도 잘 모르겠습니다.
마인크래프트의 최종 모습이 어떨지.
but I think we kind of got
some kind of rough estimate, I think.
하지만 우리는 어느정도 대략적인 모습은
그려진 것 같습니다. 저는 그렇게 생각합니다.
-The new roadmap.
-Yes.
-새 청사진
-그렇습니다.
We probably missed a bunch of things,
but I think this is a good basis.
우리가 아마 빼먹은 내용도 많을것 같지만
제 생각에는 기반은 잘 갖추어진 것 같습니다.
-Oh, there they are.
-They want to film us eating the muffins.
-오, 저기들 있네요.
-우리가 머핀을 먹는 것을 찍고 싶으시다네요.
Since we sort of missed it,
could you just explain what happened with the IGF today?
우리가 놓친 것이 있으니 오늘 IGF와
어떤 일이 있었는지 설명해 주시겠습니까?
Yeah, they announced the IGF finalists,
and Minecraft got in three categories:
네, IGF의 최종 후보들을 발표 했는데요,
마인크래프트가 세 부문에서 후보로 선정 되었습니다.
it was the main prize,
technical excellence, and design.
본상이랑, 기술 부문,
그리고 디자인 부문에서요.
So the main one, the grand one,
technical, and design; which is really cool.
그러니까 본상인 대상, 기술 부문, 디자인 부문이니까
정말 좋지 않습니까?
You know, Markus, when he e-mailed me,
he said, you know,
그러니까 Markus가 저에게 이메일을 보냈을때
그는 그러니까, 이렇게 말했어요.
"I'm hoping to win
some Independent Game Awards."
"저는 이번에 Independent Game Awards
에서 상을 좀 타기를 기대하고 있습니다."
And he didn't really know what all these awards were,
but it was sort of a big trip to America;
사실 그는 무슨 상들이 있는지 몰랐지만
그에게는 미국으로 가는 큰 여정이었으니까요.
really to, you know, meet the press,
and meet the industry for the first time.
언론사 기자들도 만나고, 업계의 사람들과
처음으로 만나보기 위해서였습니다.
And yeah, I think everyone then was starting to realize
that Minecraft wasn't some fluke,
네, 그제서야 사람들이 이제 마인크래프트가 운지 좋아서
성공한 것이 아니라는 것을 막 깨닫기 시작한 것 같습니다.
it wasn't, you know, something
that was kind of coming and going.
그것은 그러니까 뭔가 한번 왔다가
그냥 가버리는 그런 유행이 아니었으니까요.
It was building, and it was growing;
and that's what was great about it.
명성은 계속 쌓이고 있었고 커가고 있었고
그것은 대단한 일입니다.
It's this virus
that was starting to spread.
막 퍼지기 시작한
바이러스 같은 것이죠
-Hey, nice heads.
-Thank you; I have to say, it's an honor to meet you.
-머리 멋지네요.
-고맙습니다. 정말 만나뵈서 영광입니다.
-Yeah, thank you.
-네, 감사합니다.
-Hi.
-We're from high school.
-안녕하세요
-저희들은 고등학교에서 왔어요.
-We just came here to meet everyone and see--
-Oh, cool, hi.
-우리는 모두들 만나보고 보러 왔습니다.
-오, 그렇군요, 안녕하세요.
-It's so amazing to meet you.
-We all play Minecraft.
-만나뵙다니 정말 굉장해요.
-우리는 모두 마인크래프트를 해요.
-Hi, it's an honor to meet you.
-You too.
-안녕하세요, 만나뵙게 되서 영광입니다.
-저도요.
-Man, you inspire us.
-Oh, cool, awesome.
-정말 우리에게 영감을 주십니다.
-오, 그렇군요, 굉장하네요.
-I gotta shake your hand one more time.
-Oh, of course.
-저는 당신과 악수를 한번 더 해야겠습니다.
-아, 그럼요.
-Notch.
-Hi.
-Notch
-안녕하세요.
-Pleasure to meet you; my name is John.
-Hi John.
-만나서 반갑습니다. 제 이름은 John입니다.
-안녕하세요 John.
-I was wondering if you could sign this for me?
-Absolutely.
-혹시 여기다가 싸인좀 해주실 수 없을까요?
-물론이죠.
-My name is Marie.
-I'm Markus.
-제 이름은 Marie입니다.
-저는 Markus입니다.
It's amazing, and, I spend so much hours on it,
I can't believe I'm meeting you.
-정말 굉장합니다, 저는 엄창난 시간동안 했습니다.
-당신을 만나다니 믿을수가 없어요.
-Oh, cool.
-It's so fantastic, but um--congratulations.
-오, 그렇군요.
-정말 환상적이에요, 그리고 음 축하합니다.
Well, thank you.
네, 고맙습니다.
-Hello.
-Hi.
-안녕하세요.
Hello, how are you?
안녕하세요, 어떻십니까?
And it's fascinating to me
to see that happen, and you know,
이 모든것들이 일어나고 있는것이
저에게는 너무나 황홀합니다.
see someone like him show up at GDC,
not knowing what to expect, 그러니까 그와 같은 사람이 GDC에
아무런 기대 없이 갔는데,
and then just have this constant deluge of people
coming up to him, saying, "I love the game."
그냥 많은 사람들이 수시로 그에게 찾아와
"저는 그 게임을 사랑합니다."라고 말하는 것이
You know, that's when I think it probably really hit him,
that, you know, Minecraft had grown...
그러니까 그때서야 그도 깨달은것 같아요.
마인크래프트가 어느정도로 커졌는지
...into something that people weren't just playing;
it was something that people were loving.
사람들이 그냥 게임을 하는것이 아니라
그 게임을 사랑하게 되었다는 것을요.
-Should we go on?
-Yeah, yeah.
-그럼 이제 시작할까요?
-예 그러죠.
Going back to what we talked earlier about...
우리가 앞서 말하던 것으로 잠시 돌아가서....
I told you that my daughter likes Minecraft.
제 딸이 마인크래프트를 좋아한다고 말씀드렸잖아요.
I met Shigeru Miyamoto 2 years ago.
I said, "I'm going to meet the creator of Mario."
제가 2년 전에 Shigeru Miyamoto를 만났는데,
"아빠가 마리오를 창조한 사람을 만날거야."라고 말했는데
She's like, "Yeah, whatever."
딸이 "그래서, 어쩌라고요."라고 하더군요.
Now I told her I was going to meet you...
그런데 당신을 만난다고 했더니...
And she's like, "Oh~"
"오~"라고 하더라고요.
How many new friends have you made
since you became successful?
유명해지신 이후로 얼마나 많은
새로운 친구들을 사귀시었나요?
How many relatives that come out of the woodwork?
How many lost cousins?
그동안 숨어지내던 친척들 중에 몇이나 아는 척을 하던가요?
잊고 지내던 사촌들 중에 몇명?
I probably shouldn't answer that.
그 것에 대한 대답을 안하는게 좋을것 같네요.
So I only really just met you, but you seem
exceptionally cheerful, a cheerful man.
당신을 방금 만났는데도 불구하고, 당신은
상당히 유쾌한, 유쾌하신 분인것 같습니다.
You just seem a happy man, and I'm wondering
if that is because of your success.
정말 행복하신 분으로 보이는데, 혹시
거두신 성공 때문에 그런 것인가요?
Are you always
kind of quite chippy and--?
늘 그렇게 약간
신나해 하고 그러신가요?
-Jacob has known me for a long time.
-No, he's a total drag.
-Jacob은 저를 오랫동안 알아왔습니다.
-아닙니다, 이 사람은 완전 지루한 사람입니다.
No he's not.
농담입니다.
Yeah, I hope so, I try to feel so, but I still have
this kind of weird feeling that I don't really belong,
예, 그러길 바라고, 그러려고 노력은 합니다만, 아직까지는
조금 이상하고 제 자신이 있어야 할 곳에 있지 않은 느낌이고요,
and I think it's called, actually,
"The Imposter Syndrome."
그러니까 "가면현상"이라고 하는것
같은 그런 현상을 겪고 있습니다.
It's like an actual term for it,
if you're like, you're just faking it.
실제로 있는 용어로 누군가가
자신의 신분을 속일때 사용하는 말 입니다.
And I think it's gone too fast or something,
so I don't really feel like--
모든것이 너무나 빠르게 변한것 같아서
저는 아직 실감이 안납니다.
But yeah, I'm slowly trying to realize
that people actually do like the game;
하지만, 슬슬 사람들이 실제로 게임을
좋아한다는 것을 깨닫기 시작했습니다.
which is kind of a weird thing to say,
but when you're just sitting in front of your computer...
좀 이상한 말 처럼 들릴지 모르겠지만,
컴퓨터 앞에서 앉아서 그냥
...and you just see the numbers,
it's not the same thing as actually meeting the people.
여러가지 게임에 대한 수치들을 보는것과,
사람들을 직접 만나는 것과 많이 다릅니다.
Do you feel like you'll need to do a couple more games
to really feel confident in your own ability?
자신의 능력에 대해서 더 자신감이 생기려면
몇개의 게임을 더 개발해야 한다고 느끼시나요?
Yeah, I think so.
네, 아마도 그럴것 같습니다.
It's kind of weird; when I kind of grew up,
famous people, to me, like John Carmack and stuff,
이상한 것이, 제가 자라면서 알고 지낸 John Carmack과
같은 유명한 사람들 있잖습니까, 그런 사람들은 제게는
were not really like,
actual people.
알고 지내는 그런 사이가 아니었기 때문에
실제로 존재하는 사람 같지는 않았거든요.
They were like forces of nature, almost,
that just did awesome things.
그러니까 멋진 일들을 하는 자연에
존재하는 그런 힘과 같은 존재였죠.
And now people tell me, like--
not everyone, but some people say, like,
그런데 이제 사람들이, 모든 사람들은 아니지만
제게 이런 말을 해주는 사람들이 몇명 있습니다.
"Yeah, you're the Carmack of this generation."
And to me, that's--
"당신은 현 시대의 Carmack 입니다."
그리고 그것은 제게...
there's no way that can be true,
'cause that guy is...
그 말이 사실일리는 없다고 생각하지만,
그 분은 정말
...well, obviously, very talented in what he does;
and I just made a game.
정말 그분이 하던 일에 실력이 출중했으니까요.
하지만 저는 단지 게임 하나를 만들었습니다.
And I kind of realize that on the surface
it sounds like the same thing--
하지만 표면상으로는 똑같은 말
처럼 들린다는 사실은 깨닫기는 했어요,
he made a game, I made a game--
but it doesn't really feel like it's the same thing.
그 분도 게임을 만들었고 저도 게임을 만들었으니까요.
하지만 제게는 똑같은 것으로 느껴지지는 않아요.
I kind of feel that all the time,
with the success of Minecraft;
마인크래프트의 성공에도 불구하고
저는 늘 항상 느끼고 있는 것이
it's kind of hard to fully understand it,
even to this day.
아직까지도 성공 했다는 사실이
잘 믿어지지가 않습니다.
I mean, we're starting to see it because
we get so much feedback
그러니까 지금은 많은 사람들로 부터
피드백을 많이 받게 되어 이제야 조금씩 실감나요.
and so many questions from big companies,
and people want to do business with and stuff,
큰 회사들로 부터 연락이 오고, 사람들이
우리와 같이 사업이나 그런것을 하기를 바라거든요.
so we're starting to grasp that.
이제서야 좀 감이 잡힙니다.
I'm constantly thinking that maybe
this is just a really fragile thing;
저는 수시로 이것이 아마 어쩌면 일시적인
것에 지나지 않을지도 모른다고 생각해 봅니다.
that we have this attention now,
but we have no idea where we're gonna be in one year.
지금은 관심이 집중 되어 있지만, 우리도
1년 후에는 어떻게 될지 모르겠거든요.
I mean, on one hand, it would be kinda cool to have
this kind of run, and then kinda slide into obscurity again.
지금 처럼 계속 앞으로 나아간다면 좋겠지만,
어쩌면 아무것도 아닌 그런 상황으로 내리막길로 갈지도 모르죠.
I'll be like, nobody,
and just do my own thing again.
그러면 저는 다시 한번 아무도 아닌 사람이 되고
저는 그냥 그저 제 일을 할 뿐이겠죠.
I think everyone feels
a bit like that, more or less,
누구나 그런 비슷한 생각을
가질 수 있다고 생각해요.
and maybe some people don't even know
how to express that feeling.
그런데 어떤 사람들은 그 감정을 어떻게
표현해야 할지 모르는것 같기도 하고요.
But, you know, he's very, you know,
aware of his own feelings.
하지만 그는 자신의 감정에 대해서
잘 알고 있습니다.
So I think it's just that he knows how to express that,
because I can recognize that from, you know,
저는 그가 그 감정을 잘 표현할 줄 아는것 같아요
왜냐하면 저는 그것을 느낄 수 있거든요.
when he started a new job, or, you know,
people say you're good and this or that,
그러니까 그가 새 일을 시작했거나 그랬을 때
사람들은 그에게 그가 무엇을 잘하는지 말하곤 하면
and he's like, "Oh, they don't know,"
you know?
"아니야, 그들은 날 잘 몰라서 그래"
라고 말하곤 했습니다.
And really, just, you know, been lucky,
or this or that, you know?
그리고 사실은 그냥 운이 좋았다거나
그런식으로 말을 해요.
I think that's just human.
그렇게 인간적인 사람이라고 생각합니다.
Everybody, welcome to an all-new Bonus Round.
I'm Geoff Keighley,
여러분, 새롭게 생긴 보너스 라운드에 오신것을 환영합니다.
저는 Geoff Keighley 입니다.
this week, at the Game Developers Conference,
and this time,
게임 개발자 컨퍼런스에서는
이번 주에, 지금 이 시간에,
we're gonna look
at the independent game scene.
우리는 인디 게임 시장을
한번 들여다 볼 것입니다.
There've been some amazing indie games
have come out over the past few years.
최근 몇년 동안 세상에는 굉장한
인디 게임들이 몇 등장 했습니다.
We've got an all-star panel to tell us about
what's going on in the independent games movement.
우리는 유명한 전문가들을 패널로 모시고
인디 게임 개발의 현황들에 대해서 들어보겠습니다.
Although Minecraft,
you're a bit of a rock star right now,
마인크래프트는 인디 게임이라고 부르기에는
다소 많이 유명해 지기는 했지만,
Markus, with the success of Minecraft,
and all your fans out there.
Markus, 당신은 많은 팬을 누리면서
마인크래프트의 성공을 통해서
How do you look at the indie movement,
'cause you've really sort of entered the scene here,
사람들의 주목을 받게 된 사람으로써
인디 게임 개발 움직임에 대해서 어떻게 보십니까?
you know, in the past year in a big way, with Minecraft.
How do you define indie?
그러니까, 지난해 마인크래프트를 통해 봤을때
대략적으로 인디를 어떻게 정의할 수 있습니까?
Yeah, for me, I think indie is--
well, there's a lack of a label for it;
네, 제게 있어서, 인디라는 것은
사실 의미가 명확하지 않다고 생각하지만
it's kind of a concept of people
making games for the sake of making games,
사람들이 게임을 만드는 것 자체를 위해 게임을 만드는
그런 개념이라고 말 수 있을것 같고요,
or exploring games
as an art form, perhaps.
아니면 게임을 예술의 형태로
바라보는 것 정도.
I think a lot of the large studios make games
to make money, or make games to make a sequel,
제 생각에는 큰 스튜디오들에서 게임을 돈을 위해서
만들거나, 차기작을 만들기 위해 게임을 만드는것 같은데,
or to make a brand; but to make games
just for the sake of making a game.
아니면 브랜드를 만들기 위해서. 하지만
게임을 만드는것 자체를 위해서 게임을 만드는 것,
Coming from that angle,
I think that's kind of the definition of "indie" for me.
그 관점에서 일을 하는것이
제게는 그것이 "인디"의 정의라고 생각됩니다.
We're gonna get a little philosophical,
because in my opinion, games have the potential to be,
그럼 약간 철학적인 얘기를 해보자면,
개인적인 의견을 말씀드리자면 게임이 가지는 잠재력은,
what I call, the preeminent art form
of the 21st century,
21세기를 대표할 수 있는
예술의 한 분야라고 할 수 있는데요,
sort of in the way that film was in some sense
the preeminent art form of the 20th century.
영화가 20세기를 대표했던 예술의
한 분야라고 할 수 있듯이요.
I figure we're about where film was in 1905;
whereas you think about it, in 1896,
저는 지금 우리가 1905년의 영화계 수준 정도에
와 있는것 같습니다. 한번 생각해 보면, 1896년에
they first filmed Fred Ott sneezing, and like,
"Oh my gosh, it's a guy sneezing, I can play it back!"
Fred Ott의 재채기 하는 장면을 처음 찍고 사람들은 이랬습니다.
"어머나, 사람이 재채기 하는 장면을 계속 재생해서 볼 수 있네!"
But it was a long time between then
and "Birth of a Nation" in 1915 or 1917,
하지만 그때로부터 영화 "Birth of a Nation"이
나온 1915년인가 1917년 까지는 꽤 오랜 시간이 흘렀죠.
where it's kind of the first quote-unquote,
modern film, where, you know, hey,
그 영화야 말로 근대적인 형태의 영화라고
부를 수 있는데, 사람들은 말이죠
they didn't realize early on that you could film a movie
in a different sequence than you showed it;
영화의 초기 시절 까지만 해도 영화에서 보여지는 순서랑
찍는 순서랑은 상관 없다는 것을 깨닫지 못했거든요.
like the concept of editing;
they had to figure that out.
그런 편집에 대한 개념 마져도
사람들이 발굴해 내야 했습니다.
They couldn't move the--they didn't know
you could move the camera, all of these things.
그 당시에는 카메라를 움직이지도, 아니 움직여도
된다는 사실과 같은 것들을 모르고 있었습니다.
And so I feel like we're really,
really early in games, but I think they have the potential.
그런것 처럼 아직까지 게임은
발전 초기 단계에 있고, 잠재력이 많다고 봅니다.
I mean, the way people interact with art entertainment,
whether it's music, or film, </p
그러니까 사람들이 예술이나 오락을 받아들이고,
교감하는 것이 음악이든 영화든,
or literature, any of these things,
is primarily at an emotional level.
문학작품이든, 무엇이든지, 모두
감성적인 차원에서 이루어집니다.
The emotions that we support as games
is basically power fantasy right now;
우리의 게임들은 현재 강력한 판타지적
감성을 우리에게 전달해 주고 있지만
whereas if I asked you to like, you know, make a game
about two people falling in love, you'd be like...
만약 제가 두 사람이 사랑에 빠지게 되는 것을
게임으로 만들어 달라고 하면 어떻겠습니까?
...I have no idea how--
there's no way to approach that problem;
그 문제를 어떻게 접근해야 좋을지
전혀 아이디어가 떠오르지 않는다고 말씀하시겠죠.
we just don't have any idea.
And I think you see this in Minecraft, which is like--
우리는 그런 아이디어가 전혀 없습니다. 그런데
이런 아이디어들을 마인크래프트에서 엿볼 수 있는데 그것은
the thing everybody mentions
is the huge component of it,
사람들이 말하고 있는 마인크래프트의 큰
구성요소라고 할수 있는데,
but then the game play that everyone talks
about is just surviving the first night.
사실상 사람들이 실제로 말하고 있는 것은
첫날 밤을 살아 남는 것에 대한 이야기 입니다.
Like, that's the magical thing that people talk about,
and that is a very human-scale thing.
그것이 바로 사람들이 말하는 마법과 같은 것이고,
굉장히 인간적인 차원의 것입니다.
You're not saving the world;
you're just trying not to die.
세상을 구한다거나 그런것이 아니고,
그냥 죽지 않으려고 하는 것 뿐이죠.
-It's very official.
-Oh yeah.
-이제는 방송 되기만 하면 되겠군요.
-네 그렇습니다.
-Ready.
-All right, thanks guys.
-됐습니다.
-알겠습니다, 수고하셨습니다.
-Yeah, it was good.
-Awesome.
-예, 아주 좋은 시간이었습니다.
-다행이군요.
-What about you guys?
-Yeah, it was good, thank you.
-당신들은 어땠나요?
-네, 좋았습니다. 감사합니다.
Ladies and gentlemen, the Game Developers Choice
Awards will begin in a few minutes.
신사 숙녀 여러분,
시상식을 몇분 후에 시작하겠습니다.
We ask that you please
take your seats.
자리에 앉아주실 것을
부탁 드리겠습니다.
Video games...
비디오 게임들...
...video game award shows.
Which came first?
비디오 게임들과, 비디오 게임 시상식들
어느것이 먼저일까요?
In the early days of the games industry,
it really felt different than it did now.
게임 산업의 초기 시절에는 정말
지금 느껴지는 것과는 다르게 느껴졌습니다.
Mostly it felt isolated, 'cause the Internet was not around;
so you just knew the people at your company,
인터넷이 존재 하지 않았기 때문에 사람들은 같은 회사 동료 이외에는
아는 사람이 없었고, 따라서 굉장히 고독한 느낌이었습니다.
and if you're, you know, lucky, you made friends
at the Game Developers Conference;
그리고 만약에 당신이 운이 좋았다면, 게임 개발자
커퍼런스에서 친구들을 사귈 수 있었습니다.
it was like the only time during the year you'd see
other people who had the same problems as you,
그날은 당신과 똑같은 문제들을
가지고 있는 사람들이나,
or, you know,
were in the same boat as you were.
같은 배를 탄 사람들을 만날 수 있는
1년 중에 한번 뿐인 그런 날이었습니다.
So it was a lot more--kind of like islands,
like people making games...
그래서 사실은 섬에 갖혀서 사람들이
게임을 만드는것 같은 상황이었어요.
...were on their own island making their game,
and then you put it out there...
각자 자신의 섬에서 게임을 만든
후에 세상에 내놓고는...
...and you'd wait for a magazine review to come in,
and that was your feedback, you know?
... 잡지에서 후기를 남겨주기를 기다렸고,
그것 뿐이 게임에 대한 피드백 이었습니다.
But now it's like
everything is so instant.
하지만 지금은 그러니까
모든것이 즉각적이지요.
You put a game--you can put an unfinished game
up on the Internet, for example.
예를 들어 아직 완성도 되지 않은 게임을
세상에 인터넷을 통해 내놓기도 하고,
But that would be crazy;
who would do that?
하지만 누가 그런 미친
짓을 하겠습니까?
-Best Downloadable Game goes to Minecraft.
-Thank you.
-다운로드 가능한 게임중에 최고의 영광은 마인크래프트에게로.<br? -감사합니다.
And the Innovation Award goes to Minecraft.
그리고 혁신 상은 마인크래프트입니다.
And the Choice Awards for the Best Debut Game
goes to Minecraft.
그리고 최고의 데뷔를 한 게임으로 선택된
게임은 마인크래프트 입니다.
Yeah, GDC, I didn't expect us
to win in anything;
네, 사실 GDC가서 그 어떤 상도
받으리라고 생각하지는 못했습니다.
I didn't dare, even hoping, that there was just--
저는 차마 희망을 가지는것 조차 엄두를 내지 못했습니다.
well, I kind of had this, "I hope at least, something,
or I'm gonna cry."
글쎄, "그래도 무엇이라도 하나만이라도 입상하지
못하면 울것같아"라고는 생각 했지만요.
Then we won like, five awards,
which was way beyond what I even dared hoping.
그런데 우리는 5개의 상이타 타게 됐습니다.
제가 감히 상상할 수 없었던 것을 훨씬 초월한 결과였죠.
We started figuring it out when
we got to the center front table,
우리가 앞쪽 가운데 테이블에 앉게 되었을 때
무슨 일이 일어날지 한번 생각해 보려고 했어요.
something big was gonna happen,
but I still didn't dare counting on it;
뭔가 큰 일이 일어날 것 같았지만,
직감을 차마 믿을 수는 없었죠.
but then we won just a bunch of awards,
and it was just ecstatic, and we didn't know what to do.
그런데 우리는 많은 상을 타게 되었고,
황홀해서 어쩔줄 몰랐습니다.
It's still, like,
the biggest night of my life.
아직까지는 제 인생에 있어서
최고의 밤 이었습니다.
Please join me in honoring
Creative Director of Microsoft Game Studios Europe,
저와 같이 Microsoft Game Studios
Europe의 Creative Director이자
and co-founder of both Bullfrog Productions
and Lionhead Studios, Peter Molyneux.
Bullfrog Productions와 Lionhead Studios 공동 창업자
Peter Molyneux에게 존경을 표하는데 동참해 주시기 바랍니다.
I never believed,
never in my wildest dreams did I believe...
저는 평생 믿지 않았습니다.
그 어떠한 황당한 꿈속에서 조차
...that I would be standing out here
and getting a Lifetime Achievement Award.
이런 자리에 일생의 업적에 대해 상을 받는
이런 자리에 서게 될 것이라고는 믿지 못했습니다.
The very moment I first saw Minecraft,
the very second I first saw it, it was like a--
제가 마인크래프트를 처음 봤을 때,
처음 본 순간에, 저는 그랬습니다.
it was like, you know,
the world changed for me a little bit.
그러니까, 뭐랄까, 저의 세상은
약간 바뀌게 되었습니다.
What I did immediately;
I went 'round to everyone and said,
저는 바로 주변에 있는 사람들에게
가서 말했습니다.
"Oh, you gotta go and play Minecraft;
you've got to look at this game."
"꼭 마인크래프트를 해보고
어떤지 꼭 확인해 봐야 합니다."
And a lot people, a lot of my colleagues,
you know, Lionhead and Microsoft,
그랬더니 많은 사람들이, 그러니까
Lionhead와 Microsoft의 동료들이
they looked at it, and--
some people looked at it and said,
한번 살펴봤습니다, 그리고 몇몇
사람들이 살펴보더니 이렇게 말했습니다.
"This is ridiculous. Where's the tutorial,
where's the challenges, where's the--?"
"이건 최악입니다. 튜토리얼은 어디있고
게임의 목적이 뭐고, 그리고 또..."
You know, there's this list of game must-haves;
and Minecraft broke every single one of those formulas.
그러니까 게임들이 보통 가져야 하는 요소들이 있는데
마인크래프트는 그 공식 하나하나를 모두 깨고 있었습니다.
You know, it is like--it is, in a way,
a social Lego, when Lego used to be a creative toy;
그러니까 어떻게 보면, 사교적인 요소가 섞인 레고와 같은 것이죠
레고가 창의적인 장난감이었던 것을 생각해 보면 말이죠.
which I don't think it is so much anymore,
because it's much more prescriptive.
지금은 뭐든지 정해진 대로 만드는것 같아서
더이상 그렇지는 않은것 같지만요.
It's really interesting how Lego at the moment
is like traditional games design:
현재 이 시점의 레고는 전통적으로 게임이
디자인 되었던 방식과 비슷하다는 점은 참 흥미로운것 같습니다.
it's buy the box, open the box,
turn to the instruction sheet, make the model,
박스를 구입해서 뜯은 후에 설명서를
보고 조립을 한 후에
stick it on the shelf,
buy the next box.
선반에 놔두고
다른 박스를 구매하죠
That's exactly like traditional game design, you know:
buy the game, go through the challenges,
그것이 전통적인 게임이 디자인된 방식입니다.
그러니까 게임을 사서, 게임의 도전 과제를 보고
finish the challenges, stick it on the shelf,
buy the next game;
주어진 목표를 다 이루고, 선반에 보관하고
그 다음 게임을 구매 합니다.
where Lego used to be just a big box of bricks,
and you used to take the bricks,
그 반면 예전의 레고는 블록 가득한
상자였고 블록들을 가져다가,
pour them on the carpet, and then make stuff;
and that's exactly what Minecraft is.
카페트에 쏟아 부은 후에, 무엇인가를 만들었죠.
마인크래프트가 바로 그런것과 비슷합니다.
There was no instruction booklet;
but that's really what this points to,
사용 설명서도 없지만,
그것이 바로 시사하는 바가 있다고 보는데,
is just how conventional game studios, how complacent
they were with the games that they were making.
전통적인 게임 스튜디오들이 그들이 현재 만들고 있는 게임들을
통해 얼마나 안주하고 변화하지 않고 있는지 알 수 있습니다.
And we need, this industry desperately needs
things like Minecraft to come along and say,
그래서 우리가, 그리고 게임 업계가 간절하게
필요한 것은 마인크래프트와 같은 게임이 등장해서
slap us 'round the face and say,
"Hang on a second. All those things...
쫓아다니면서 우리의 낯짝을 때리며
"잠깐만요. 모든 것이...
...that you thought were absolutely certain in your life?
They're not certain anymore."
...당신이 인생에서 확고히 당연하다고 믿었던 것들이
더이상 당연한 것이 아닙니다."라고 말해 주는 것입니다.
Definitely grown;
I think we all are.
분명히 성장했죠
우리 모두 그런것 같아요.
I mean, it's an experience that I think very few people
will ever experience, you know.
제 말은, 저희들이 경험했던 것은
정말 소수의 사람만이 경험할 수 있는 것이니까요.
There are few companies in the world
that have experienced this kind of growth.
그리고 세계적으로도 이런 성장세를
보인 회사도 몇 안되니까요.
It's very inspiring.
굉장히 영감을 주는 경험입니다.
So we're kind of trying to figure out exactly what
we're gonna do with the company now.
그래서 우리는 앞으로 회사를 두고 어떻게
해야 할지 계속 생각하고 있는 중입니다.
Okay, so, we've discussed this before--
네, 이미 저희들이 의논을 전에 했었지만...
I think as soon as--
저는 가능한 빨리...
I sometimes find it hard to concentrate.
저는 종종 집중하는 것에 어려움을 겪고 있습니다.
I don't think we have the grand master plan
of world domination; this seems fun now, let's go for it.
우리 중에는 세계 정복을 위해 계획을 가지고 일하는
사람은 없습니다. 일단 재미 있어 보이니, 한번 해보는 것입니다.
And I think that's great.
그래서 좋은것 같습니다.
If I would have been Markus,
I would have, you know,
제가 만약에 Markus였다면요
아마도 저는 그러니까,
doing blow off hookers' asses;
that's what I've been telling people.
성매매 업소에서 돈이나 쓰고 앉아있었을 거라고
저는 사람들에게 말하고 다녔습니다.
But seeing how he still remains
so humble and grounded in reality,
하지만 그가 여전히 얼마나 겸손하고,
현실적으로 일하는지를 바라고보 있으면,
that's extremely reassuring
for someone like me, you know?
저같은 사람에게는 큰 안도감을
줍니다. 무슨 말인지 아십니까?
I'm very pleased.
아주 만족스럽습니다.
Good.
좋아요.
-Oh, hello Notch.
-Hello.
-아, 안녕하세요 Notch
-안녕하세요.
We had a great party on Thursday,
celebrating two million.
우리는 목요일에 이백만을 기념하는
성대한 파티를 갖았습니다.
Do you want to sum it up?
어땠는지 한번 정리해 주시겠습니까?
I was just gonna ask if it was good,
'cause I don't remember it.
저는 어땠는지 기억이 잘 안나서
오히려 제가 어땠는지 물어보려고 했는데요.
Oh, okay, yeah.
Anyone else?
아, 그렇군요.
다른분들은 할말 없습니까?
Cocaine's one helluva drug.
코카인은 정말 최고의 마약입니다.
I'm really envious of the new crop
of game-makers out there, like Markus and other people,
저는 요즘에 Markus나 그와 같이 요즘에 게임을
막 만들기 시작한 사람들이 부럽습니다.
who are just doing it themselves; like all by themselves,
with maybe with one or two people on their team;
그들은 스스로 하고 있습니다. 정말로 모든것을 혼자
또는 한두명 더 해서 팀을 이루어서 다 하고 있습니다.
'cause they keep the cost down, they can self-publish,
and they've just made so much more money.
비용을 최소화 함으로써, 그들 스스로 발매함으로써
더 많은 돈을 벌 수가 있었습니다.
That's the secret; when you take
someone else's money to make your game,
바로 그것이 비밀입니다. 다른 사람의
돈을 가져다가 게임을 만든다면
you have to give them
all your money after you're done.
게임이 완성되면 그 돈을 다시
되돌려줘야 합니다.
Not that I'm bitter.
그 사실이 씁쓸하다는 것은 아닙니다만.
I think we all want to stay small, and we want to
stay in control, and we want to stop the world looking in;
제 생각에는 모두 작게 유지하고 싶어 하고, 지속적으로
통제할 수 있기를 바라고, 외부에서 들여다 보지 않기를 바라지만
it's very, very, very,
very hard to do so.
그것은 너무나, 너무나, 너무나,
너무나 어려운 일입니다.
I mean, I think the perfect size for me
is once you reach over 20 people,
그러니까 제 생각하기에 이상적인 크기의
조직인 20명을 넘게 된다면
that's when it gets really tough;
because then you need to have...
그때 부터 굉장히 어려워집니다.
그 이유는 그때부터...
...another layer of people
to manage the people that are there.
...조직에 단계를만들어 사람들을
관리하기 시작해야 하기 때문이죠.
And when you can all fit in one office,
and you can stick your head up and say,
하지만 만약에 모두 같은 사무실에 모여서
일할 수 있다면, 고개를 들어서
"Oh, what's that you're working on?" or,
"Look at this everybody," that's a perfect size.
"오, 지금 당신이 일하고 있는것이 뭐지요?" 아니면
"모두들 이것좀 보세요"라고 할 수 있는 조직의 크기가 제일 좋죠.
But once you get over that,
it's really tough.
하지만 그 크기를 넘어서기만 하면
아주 어렵게 됩니다.
So if I was doing it all again,
I would say exactly what Markus is saying;
그래서 제가 만약 모든 것을 다시 시작하게 된다면
지금 Markus가 말하는 그대로를 말하게 될 것입니다.
I would say, "I'm gonna stay small."
"우리는 작게 유지할 것입니다."라고요.
I don't want, like, a big office with like, 150 people;
it kind of turns into a 9-5 job.
저는 150명이 일하는 그런 큰 사무실에서 일하고 싶지 않습니다.
그렇게 되면 9시에 출근해서 5시에 퇴근하는 그런 조직이 되고 말아요.
I would say I'm afraid of doing what Id Software did,
but I'm not gonna say that,
Id Software사가 하는것 처럼 하기가 두렵다고나 할까요?
하지만 이런말 하면 안될것 같네요.
'cause that's rude
against Id Software.
Id Software사에게 무례한
발언이 될테니까요.
But I mean, their games
aren't as fun as they used to be.
하지만 그들의 게임은
예전의 게임들 만큼 재미있지 않아요.
I mean, they look better.
더 좋아 보일 수는 있겠죠.
I mean, the MegaTexture stuff is really amazing,
but I'd rather play a fun game.
물론 MegaTexture 기술과 같은 것은 아주 대단합니다.
하지만 저는 차라리 재미있는 게임을 하겠습니다.
And I want us to make fun games,
not just big production games.
그래서 저는 우리가 대형 프로덕션의 산물인 게임
보다는 재미있는 게임을 만들기를 바랍니다.
Ideally for me, it would just be like,
me and a box of Red Bull.
이상적으로는, 그냥 Red Bull 한 상자만 있으면
혼자서도 일할 수 있을것 같습니다.
I'm gonna play dark ritual,
get some--two cultists.
저는 어둠의 의식을 수행하고,
두명의 광신자를 데려가겠어요.
And someone could, like, discard--
you could discard this.
그럼 누군가가, 그러니까, 버릴수...
당신이 이것을 버리면 되겠네요.
Yeah, I will next time, yeah.
네, 다음번에 버릴거에요. 암 그렇고 말고요.
-What's the next big event coming up, E3?
-Yeah;
-이제 다가오는 가장 큰 일은 무엇인가요? E3인가요?
-네
We have the E3,
which is basically,
네, E3가 가장 크네요.
E3는 기본적으로
not for indie game developers at all;
it's just about spending money, and launching titles.
인디 게임 개발자들을 위한 것은 아니죠
주로 큰 돈을 뿌리면서 새로운 타이틀을 출시하는 행사죠.
I have to go, apparently.
보시다시피, 저도 가야합니다.
I mean, it's a cool trip
and I really like going to the E3, but I kinda want to code.
그러니까 멋진 여행이 될 것이고
E3에 가게 된 것이 좋지만, 저는 코딩을 하고 싶어요.
Oh cool! That's why I--
that's why I recognize you.
아 멋져요! 그래서 제가...
당신을 알아봤군요!
I was like, do I know him?
I think I know you, what's happening?
저는 설마, 내가 저 사람을 알고 있나?
알고 있는것 같은데, 무슨 일이지? 이러고 있었어요.
To ensure we can accommodate
everyone's carry-on baggage,
여러분 모두의 캐리온 가방을
위한 공간이 제공될 수 있도록
please place smaller items
under the seat in front of you...
작은 짐은 앞좌석 밑에
보관하여 주시기 바라고...
...and larger items
in the overhead bins above your row.
...큰 짐은 앉아계신 좌석 상단에
있는 보관함에 넣어주시기 바랍니다.
Yeah, we started the podcast in 2010,
in October, 2010.
네, 저희들이 2010년에 팟캐스트를
시작했어요. 2010년 10월에요.
This is maybe about a month
after we actually started playing the game.
그게 아마도 우리들이 게임을 하기
시작한지 약 한달 후쯤 이었을 겁니다.
So in a month's time,
we knew it was something special enough...
약 한달 동안의 기간에 우리들은
게임이 충분히...
...that we wanted to devote our lives to talking about,
and to producing a show.
...우리가 인생을 바쳐서 게임에 대해서 이야기 하는
쇼를 만들고 싶을 정도로 특별하다고 생각했습니다.
So we did know it was going to be
something big and something special.
우리는 이 게임이 대박을 칠 만큼
특별하다는 것을 이미 알고 있었습니다.
And I forgot what you asked already.
그리고 원래 질문이 뭐였는지 까먹었네요.
This is for people who don't know;
this is where what we've been doing...
모르는 사람들을 위해서 잠간 설명을 하자면
지금 여기는 우리가 지난 1주일 동안...
...over the past week
since the last episode.
...마지막 에피소드 이후로
우리가 작업한 장소입니다.
But I've also been watching my son play Minecraft,
which has been fascinating, because--
저는 제 아들도 마인크래프트를 하는 것을
봤는데, 흥미로웠습니다. 왜냐하면...
Like the Shaft podcast guys, for example, I'm like,
"Wow, this is more than an hour just about Minecraft."
Shaft 팟캐스트 사람들 있잖아요, 그 사람들 보면서 그랬습니다.
"와우, 이건 정말 마인크래프트 하나에 대해서 한시간 이상을 말하는군."
It still blows my mind; it's like, wow,
they're actually just talking about this game.
아직도 놀랍습니다. 그러니까 정말로
그들은 진짜로 이 게임에 대해서만 얘기합니다.
It's amazing.
놀랍습니다.
So this is from Nergock who said,
"I have to thank you guys for suggesting...
자 이것은 Nergock님 께서 보낸 사연인데요,
"저는 여러분께 마인크래프트를 하면서...
...listening to a book while playing Minecraft.
It's greatly improved my Minecraft enjoyment..."
...오디오 북을 듣는 것을 권해주신 것에 대해 감사드립니다.
제가 마인크래프트를 더욱 즐길 수 있게 되었습니다..."
And we try to be on time, never skip one;
except we missed one episode...
저희들은 항상 제 시간에 빼먹지 않고 하려고 하는데
딱 한번 예외적으로 에피소드를 빼먹었네요...
...because tornadoes ripped up our city;
but that was the one we missed.
...토네이도가 도시를 갈기락리 찢어버리는 바람에요
하지만 그때 딱 한번 빼먹었습니다.
And honestly, when that happened,
the community got together, and,
그리고 솔직히 말씀드리면 그때 무슨 일이
있었는가 하면, 커뮤니티가 스스로 뭉쳐서
awesome girls, too, Tory Love pulled all this information
from the community and basically--
그중에는 물론 멋진 여자분들도 있었는데, Tory Love가
커뮤니티로부터 온갖 정보들을 다 모아서
it was an appreciation show for us, that she gathered
all this material so we didn't have to do anything.
우리 쇼에 대한 감사를 표하는 쇼를 만들어서, 우리가
아무것도 안해도 되겠금 방송 소재들을 그녀가 다 모았어요.
I mean, I'm getting chills
just thinking about it right now;
저는 아직도 그때만 생각하면
몸에 전율이 느껴집니다.
it's just an amazing community
around the show and around this game.
게임과 쇼를 둘러싼 아주 멋진
커뮤니티 입니다.
Community is always going to be, probably,
the most important thing when it comes to Minecraft...
커뮤니티는 아마도 마인크래프트에 대해서
논하는데 있어서 항상 중요한 요소가 될것입니다.
...because that's what makes it
bigger than itself.
왜냐하면 커뮤니티가 마인크래프트를
더욱 크게 키워주기 때문이죠.
It's very cool to see, you know,
people are so involved and really, like,
사람들이 이 일에 실제로 참여하는 모습을
볼 수 있다는 것은 정말 멋진 일 같습니다.
making something
that's just about this game.
오로지 이 게임을 위해서
무엇인가를 만들어가는 모습이요.
I do think that there is something to be said for the fact
that so many people are excited about the game,
많은 사람들이 이 게임에 대해서 그렇게 열광하고
각자의 열정을 다른 사람들과 나눈다는 사실을 두고
and they are excited to share
their excitement with other people.
저는 게임에 대해서 이야기할 만한
것들이 있다고 생각합니다.
And I do think
there's a synergy from that.
저는 그런 활동들을 통해서
시너지 효과가 생긴다고 생각합니다.
I've never seen
anything like this.
평생 이런것은
본 적이 없습니다.
It is--it has so much universal appeal
over so many different kinds of people;
이 게임은 굉장히 다양한 사람들이
일반적으로 매력을 느끼고 있습니다.
I've never seen anything like it.
정말 이런것은 한번도 본적이 없습니다.
I mean, Minecraft, because
it's such an open experience, an open world,
그러니까 마인크래프트는 개방된 세상에서
너무나도 개방된 경험들을 제공하기 때문에
kind of naturally lends itself
to be populated by these sub-cultures...
그 문화는 자연스럽게 다른 문화와
접목되어 분포 되기도 합니다.
...of mission and creators,
or podcasters, or live-streamers.
예를 들면 개인 콘텐츠 제작자나
팟 캐스터, 또는 인터넷 생방송를 통해서요.
Yeah, Yogscast is certainly
one of them, I think.
네, Yogscast도 당연히 그런
예라고 할 수 있을것 같습니다.
We met because we both
were in the same World of Warcraft guild.
우리는 월드 오브 워크래프트에서 같은
길드에 있어서 만나게 되었습니다.
So we met in a thoroughly nerdy way
and ended up doing a thoroughly nerdy job,
그래서 우리는 괴짜들 다운 만남을 유지했고
결국에는 굉장히 별난 직업을 갖게 되었습니다.
which is, effectively,
playing Minecraft.
바로 마인크래프트를
직접 하는 것이죠.
-That's our job, isn't it?
-Well, it's not just--video production, and--
-그것이 우리의 직업 맞죠?
-엄밀히 말하자면, 단순히 그것은 아니고, 영상제작을...
but basically we do get paid to play Minecraft.
하지만 우리는 마인크래프트 하는 것으로 수입이 생깁니다.
-Dude, there's something up there in that cave.
-Is there?
-여보게, 저 위로 동굴 쪽에 뭔가 있는것 같.
-그렇소?
Yeah, it's a green thing, look, bouncing.
그렇소, 초록색이고, 보시오, 펄쩍펄쩍 뛰고 있소.
-Oh, Christ almighty, it's a creeper.
-It's gone.
-어머나 세상에, 크리퍼군.
-이제 사라졌군
-Yeah, those are very, very bad.
-It's gone, Simon.
-저것들은 굉장히 나쁘오.
-이제 사라졌소, Simon.
They follow you and they explode;
don't go in towards it; it'll see you.
그들은 당신을 쫓아다니다 폭발하오
그쪽으로 가지 마시오, 당신을 보게 될 것이오.
We don't script anything; we just play the game
and record it and put it on YouTube.
우리는 대사를 미리 짜거나 하지 않고, 그냥 게임을
하면서 녹화를 하고 유튜브에 올립니다.
So, a lot of people watch it.
상당히 많은 사람들이 보더군요.
Good morning!
So we hit a million subscribers this morning.
좋은 아침!
우리는 오늘 아침 구독자 수가 백만이 되었습니다.
I'm gonna go
and wake Simon up with one of these.
저는 가서 Simon을
이것을 사용해 깨울 것입니다.
Morning Simon,
I've got you a coffee.
좋은 아침 Simon
내가 커피를 가져왔어요.
You all right?
괜찮아요?
But it doesn't pay, you know, super well;
you only get sort of,
하지만 수입이 많지는 않아요, 아주 짭잘한 정도는
아니고, 그러니까 어떤 식이냐면
nought point nought, nought, nought one cent
per, you know, view. 한번 조회 될 때마다
영 쩜 영, 영, 영, 일 센트 벌어요.
But because we have a million views on a video,
that actually ends up adding up to enough.
하지만 한 영상당 백만회의 조회수 정도 발생해서
겨우 적당한 정도의 수입이 생깁니다.
So it is a big audience of people, and I think we probably
do it a bit better than most, which is why we're just--
그러니까 상당히 큰 청취자들이 있고요, 아마도 우리가
다른 사람들 보다 잘 해서 그런것 같아요. 그러지 않고서야...
But we're still modest.
하지만 그래도 대단하지는 않습니다.
It's kind of like a journey for me,
playing Minecraft and watching...
저에게는 일종의 탐험을 떠나는것과 같아요.
마인크래프트를 하거나 구경하면서
...how it's changed
over the months and months,
지난 몇달 동안
변화된 것을 보면서
and thinking in a few months' time
how different is it gonna be?
앞으로 몇달 후에는 얼마나
바뀔까라고 생각하죠.
And I guess it is kind of nice to have
almost feel like you're a part of that,
그리고 뭐가 좋냐 하면요, 마치 내가
그 변화의 과정의 일부분이 된다고 느끼는 것인데,
because you've
experienced that as a gamer.
게이머로서 변화의 과정을
겪으니까 그럴만하죠.
And since you're in debug mode;
우리가 지금 디버깅 모드에 있으니까
you can just change the code and it just
instantly changes, which is very, very efficient.
코드를 약간만 수정 한다면
즉각적으로 적용되어 굉장히 효율적이죠.
Yeah, I can do anything; we can make arrows explode
when they hit the ground instead.
아무것이나 다 할 수 있습니다. 화살이 땅에 닿으면
폭발 하도록 바꿀 수도 있습니다.
Arrow in ground; there we go.
땅에다가 화살을 쏘고, 자 보세요.
When doing a game, it's more about
what to expect from a game...
게임을 만들 때에는, 게임을 통해서
무엇을 기대할 수 있는지가 중요합니다.
...and trying to play around with those expectations;
that's kind of the most fun part.
그리고 그런 기대감을 조율하는 것이
가장 신나는 일인것 같습니다.
Let's give it a bigger explosion!
한번 더 큰 폭발을 읽으켜 볼까요!
There we go.
자 갑니다.
Oh, is that thunder?
어머나, 천둥이 쳤나요?
-I think it's about 9,000.
-9,000?
-한 9,000장 정도 되는것 같습니다.
-9,000장이요?
Or something;
it's insane.
그정도 될겁니다.
굉장합니다.
Minecon is basically a celebration
of the launch of Minecraft.
마인콘은 마인크래프트의 런칭을
기념하는 행사입니다.
Do you think it's reasonable
time to do it in November?
혹시 11월에 행사를 하는것이
좋다고 생각하나요?
Yeah, we can--
네, 아마도...
It would be cool to sort of do a live deployment on stage
when they deploy the one dot o version.
만약에 행사장 무대에서 1.0 버전의 배포를
실제로 진행이 된다면 멋질것 같네요.
That would be cool.
그것 참 멋지네요.
Yeah, I will get nervous.
네, 저는 긴장될 겁니다.
We haven't put up the site
where people can register yet,
아직 사람들이 등록할 수 있는
사이트를 열지 않았습니다.
so we have no idea how many are gonna show up,
and we signed the papers already with the hotel.
그래서 얼마나 많은 사람들이 행사에 참여하게 될지는
아직 모르는 상태고, 이미 호텔의 행사장은 계약했습니다.
I mean, at least a couple of hundred should show up,
I think, but I have no idea.
글세요, 적어도 이백명 정도는 행사에 참여하지
않을까요? 잘 모르겠네요.
It is a collaborative medium;
developers and gamers collaborate.
이곳은 개발자와 게이머들이
협력할 수 있는 매체가 됩니다.
We are makers, we are creators,
and that's why we're here today;
우리는 만들기도 하고, 창조하기도 하고
그래서 우리 모두 오늘 여기 모였습니다.
because we're gonna celebrate
that collaboration between developers and gamers.
개발자와 게이머들 간의 협력 관계를
우리는 기념할 것입니다.
So I'm very, very grateful for everyone
who's come to join us today,
그래서 오늘 여기 모인 여러분
한분 한분께 감사 드립니다.
and I think it is particularly fitting
that our first presenter today is Mojang;
오늘 첫 발표는 Mojang에서 하는데, 제 생각에는
첫 발표자로는 아주 적합하지 않나 생각합니다.
because it's hard to imagine a game that would,
like Minecraft, that would flourish,
그 이유는, 지금까지는 마인크래프트와 같은 게임이
이렇게 발전할 수 있으리라고 상상하기 힘들었기 때문입니다.
because it breaks so many conventions and basically
hands the creative keys over to the gamers.
그동안의 일반적인 통념들을 따르지 않고
창의성에 대한 부분을 게이머들에게 맡겼긴 것
And that is truly revolutionary.
그것이야 말로 혁명이 아닌가 생각합니다.
And so I am very, very pleased to introduce
Markus "Notch" Persson and Lydia Winters,
여러분에게 기쁜 마음으로 소개시켜드릴
Markus "Notch" Persson과 Lydia Winter는
who are gonna show you
the Minecraft Adventure update.
업데이트 된 마인크래프트 모험을 선보일 것입니다.
Please welcome them.
그들을 환영해 주세요.
Minecraft is why we do what we do,
because it--
우리가 마인크래프트를 하는 이유는
그 자체에 있습니다. 왜냐하면
you are literally looking into the future
when you see Minecraft, you know?
마인크래프트를 보고 있으면, 미래를
들여다 볼 수 있으니까요. 아시겠어요?
Like I said, we've always had these genres,
we always had the traditional stuff,
이미 말했듯이 여러 장르들의 게임이 있었고
그 장르들은 전형적인 것이 되었습니다.
but this is the future of gaming,
you know?
하지만 이것은 미래의 게임 방식입니다
안그럴까요?
This collaboration, this emphasis on creativity,
on freedom.
같이 협력하는것, 그리고 창의성에
중점을 둔 자유도
And it's thrilling to be able to be here and say,
"Yes, I was there when it happened."
그리고 지금 이 자리에 서서 "그래 나는 이 모든 일이
일어나는 현장에 있었어"라고 말할 수 있다는 것이 흥분됩니다.
He obviously knew he was creating building blocks;
but I don't think anybody could have expected...
그는 당연히 블록 만들기 게임을 만들고 있다는 것을 알고 있었죠.
하지만 누구도 예측할 수는 없었을 것입니다...
...how ready so many millions of people were
to take those building blocks and say,
...수백만명의 사람들이 이 블록 만들기를
가지고 즐길 준비가 되어
"Okay, I'm gonna create stuff in the game."
I don't think anybody could see that coming.
"그래, 나는 게임에서 무엇인가를 만들거야."
라고 말할 것이라고 누구라도 예측하지는 못했을 것입니다.
Sorry, that was
really horrible.
미안하지만 정말
안좋은 상황이었습니다.
-Oh, it’s okay.
-It’s a good thing I left...
-아, 괜찮습니다.
-제가 자리를 뜨기를 잘한것 같습니다...
...because you would have been
very alarmed...
... 그러지 않았다면 아주 많이
놀라셨을 것입니다.
...that I was gonna die.
... 제가 죽을것만 같았거든요.
The fact in God games
you kind of own the world...
God Game(게임의 한 장르)에서 조차
당신이 누리는 있는 세상이 있다는 사실은...
...isn’t as important
as owning your own house.
...은 당신이 집을 소유하고 있다는
사실보다 중요하지 않습니다.
And that idea of building,
and creating,
그래서 뭔가 만들어야 하는 사상,
그리고 창조해야 한다는 것,
and almost moding,
as part of the gaming experience,
그리고 게임을 경험하는 동안
게임을 변화 시켜야 한다는 것,
is why it’s far better
than a God game,
그것이 이 게임이 God Game보다
훨씬 좋은 이유 입니다.
and a game
that I’ve done.
그리고 제가 만든
게임들 보다도요.
Sure.
그렇습니다.
You’re, uh--
어, 그러니까...
No, for sure.
네, 그렇습니다.
It’s fact.
사실입니다.
Because of Minecraft,
I think, it has changed...
마인크래프트로 인해서
저는 제가 변했다고 생각합니다.
...my view of what I do
on a day to day basis.
제가 하루하루 하는
일들을 바라보는 관점이라든지.
I still really believe
that I have got one great game.
저는 아직도 저로부터 좋은
게임이 나올 것이라 믿습니다.
You know, inside one great game
idea that I can inspire a team...
그러니가 좋은 게임에 대한 아이디어로
저는 팀에게 영감을 줄 수 있고...
...to turn into a real
idea in me.
... 그 과정을 통해 제 아이디어는
구체화 될 것입니다.
Well, everyone in the studio
is huge, huge fans...
스튜디오에 있는 모든 사람들이
마인크래프트의 아주아주 큰...
...of Minecraft.
... 팬 입니다.
Oh cool!
오~ 멋집니다.
It is amazing when
you do something like that,
당신이 그런 일을 함으로써
놀라웠던 것은
and then it becomes this expression
of everybody’s creativity.
사람들이 자신의 창의력을 표현하는
하나의 수단이 되었다는 것입니다.
It is such a cool place
to build,
아주 멋진 매체인것 같습니다.
무엇을 만든다든지,
and grow a community,
and meet friends.
커뮤니티를 키운다거나
새로운 사람을 만나기 위해서요.
I wouldn’t even call Minecraft
a game anymore.
저는 더이상 마인크래프트를
게임이라고 부르지 않겠습니다.
It’s so much further
than that.
이미 그 이상의 것이
되었습니다.
It’s a platform.
하나의 플랫폼 입니다.
It’s a platform for us to develop
our architectural side,
우리의 건축에 대한 자질이나,
창의적인 본성을 발달시키기 위한
our creative nature.
하나의 플랫폼 입니다.
It let’s us be ourselves,
communicate with people,
우리 본연의 모습 그대로
사람들과 소통하고,
and create things
that we maybe didn’t think...
그리고 평생 만들 수
있으리라 상상하지도...
...we ever could,
but now we can.
... 못했던 것들을,
이제는 만들 수 있습니다.
Anytime I get on that server,
I get astounded by the imagination,
서버에 접속할 때마다
저는 사람들의 상상력에 놀랍니다.
the creativity of the people
that are on there,
이 세상에 있는 사람들의
창의성은 정말
and my jaw just
hits the ground.
제 입이 떡하고
벌어지게 합니다.
I just can’t believe
what the people;
저는 그냥 믿을 수가 없습니다.
어떻게 사람들이
A, have the design sense
to accomplish.
그런 것을 성취할 수 있는
디자인 감각을 가질 수 있는지.
I can’t do it.
저는 할 수 없거든요.
I don’t know if it’s
just me,
그냥 저만 그런 것인지는
잘 모르겠습니다만
but I’m looking at this stuff,
and like, “Wow!”
사람들의 작품을 보고 있자면
"와우" 하고 탄성이 절로 나옵니다.
And I’ll tell them.
그리고 사람들에게 말하죠.
I’ll say, “This is fabulous.”
"정말 기막히군요"라고요.
“This is fantastic.” "이것은 환상적입니다."
“How do you do this?”
"어떻게 이런 것을 할 수 있지?"
Hi there, everybody!
여러분 안녕하세요!
This is Halkun,
and I’m gonna demonstrate...
저는 Halkun입니다.
저는 지금 시범을 보여드릴텐데요...
to you how I really don’t play
Minecraft like other people.
제가 보통 사람들과는 다르게 어떻게
마인크래프트를 즐기는 보여드리겠습니다.
Now, first thing you’re gonna notice
is I’m kinda staring at a corner...
지금, 처음으로 알아차리셨을 것이
제가 어느 한쪽 구석의...
of a very,
very deep well.
아주 깊은 우물
에서 시작한다는 것입니다.
And it’s made out
of bedrock,
이 우물은 기반암으로
만들어져 있고요,
and it’s very, very high,
and I’m sure you’re probably thinking,
아주 아주 높습니다.
아마 무엇을 생각하고 계실지 알것 같습니다.
“Why Halkun, that is a very,
very deep well.”
"Halkun, 그것 참 깊은
우물을 만들었구나."
And I’m gonna show you
the reason why.
제가 왜 만들었는지
보여드리겠습니다.
It is currently holding...
지금 무엇인가 지탱하고 있는데...
...this!
... 이것입니다.
This is a 1:1 scale model
of the Starship Enterprise.
이것은 스타쉽 엔터프라이즈(스타트랙에 나오는 우주선)의
1:1 실물 크기 모형입니다.
I just got finished putting
the framework together.
이제 막 틀을 조립하는 것을
마무리 지었습니다.
I haven’t slept yet,
so I’m gonna be a little loopy...
잠을 못 잤기 때문에
제가 이것을 보여드리는 동안...
...as I show you what
I’ve got here.
... 약간 이상할 수
있습니다.
So, as you can see there’s
still some scaffolding still up there.
여기 보시다시피 저 위에 여전히
공사를 위해 설치한 발판이 있습니다.
So, why don’t we take a walk,
shall we?
자 그럼 나들이를 떠나 보는 것은
어떻겠습니까?
I reversed 6502 code
for fun.
저는 6502 코드를 취미로
분석했습니다.
So, I have like disassembled
source code...
그래서, 소스코드를 디스어셈블
하는 작업들도 했는데,
...from Final Fantasy I.
파이널 판타지 1탄도 했었습니다.
I have disassembled
source code...
그리고 또 소스코드를 디스어셈블한
것 중에...
...from ProDOS
for the Apple II that I’ve taken apart.
제가 임의로 분해한 Apple II를
위한 ProDOS도는 있습니다.
And that’s what I do,
I find these programs,
그런 것들이 제가 하는 일입니다.
프로그램들을 찾아서,
and take them apart.
분해하고 분석합니다.
I’ve been, I’ve been reverse
engineering applicate software...
저는 그동안 응용 프로그램을
리버스 엔지니어링한 기간이
...for like ten years.
약 10년 정도 됩니다.
I’m actually active
in a community...
그리고 저는 꽤
활발하게...
...where we’ve been disassembling
Final Fantasy VII...
... 파이널 판타지 7탄을 디스어셈블하고
있는 커뮤니티에서 활동하고 있습니다.
for the last decade.
지난 10년동안.
Pretty much I’m all over
the map when it comes...
이런 것들에 관련된 것이라면
제 흔적을...
...to just things.
... 찾아보실 수 있습니다.
Intellectual property law,
I do reverse engineering,
지적 재산권 관련된일,
리버스 엔지니어링 일,
I do the marketing.
마케팅도 제가 직접 하고요.
So, it’s because I live in
a very tiny apartment,
그것은 아마도 제가 작은
아파트에 살아서,
and I’m often bored.
자주 지루해 지기 때문일 것입니다.
Um, let me see if I can find
my Enterprise.
흠, 제가 제 엔터프라이즈 호를
찾을 수 있는지 한번 볼까요?
So we’re sitting at...
그러니까 저 지금...
8,984,531,
and I need to update these badly.
8,984,531회의 조회수를 기록하고 있고, 저는 이것을
빨리 업데이트 해야겠네요.
What are some of the comments
here that you have?
여기에 올라온 코멘트들 중에는
어떤 것들이 있나요?
Nerd!
제가 너드라는군요!
I need a girlfriend!
저는 여자친구가 필요하다는 글!
What a geek!
엄청난 괴짜군요!
The Virgin Diaries,
because evidently...
제가 전차남 같은 남자라고
하는 글도 있는데,
...I’m a virgin, too.
사실입니다.
Uh, I don’t think you guys
have never really appreciated...
아마도 사람들이 제가 만든
엔터프라이즈 호의...
...how absolutely huge
the Enterprise is,
... 절대적인 크기에 대해서 깨닫는
사람은 없는것 같아요.
but I don’t know,
this is kind of a shock to you.
글쎄요, 여러분들에게 제가
얼마나 큰 충격을 줄 수 있는지 모르겠지만.
This thing is fucking enormous.
이것은 엄청 큽니다.
People who don’t play Minecraft
just looked at this,
마인크래프트를 즐기지 않는 사람들은
이것을 보고 그냥,
and go, “What on earth
did that nerd do?”
"도대체 이 너드는 무엇을
한 것이지?"라고 하더군요.
And a lot of people,
when they saw this too,
그리고 많은 사람들도
이것을 봤을때도 그랬어요,
they saw the video,
and they never--
영상을 보고는,
마인크래프트가
They didn’t know when Minecraft was
getting all trendy,
유행이 되기 시작한 것도
모르고서는
and everyone’s like,
“I don’t wanna play.”
많은 사람들이
"난 그 게임 안할래"라고 하거나
“It sounds like everyone’s
just getting on the band wagon.”
"사람들이 그냥 요란하게
유행을 좀 타는것 같군"라고 했죠.
And I remember when someone
saw my video,
그런데 어떤 사람이 제
영상을 본 후에
and they posted underneath it,
“Okay, I get it.”
"아, 이제 알겠네."라고 댓글을
달았던 것이 기억이 납니다.
“I understand now.”
"이제서야 이해가 가네."
“Now I see why this is such
a game that--
이제서야 사람들이 왜
이 게임을 그렇게...
why everyone’s playing
this game.
모두들 왜 이 게임을 즐기는지
그 이유가 보이네요.
Before when you would go
on YouTube,
예전에는 만약에 당신이
유튜브로 가서,
and you saw somebody
who modeled the Enterprise,
누군가가 엔터프라이즈 호를
모델링 한 것을 당신이 봤다면
you’d think,
“Wow, that’s incredible.”
"와, 대단하다."
라고 생각했겠죠.
I could never do that,
I don’t have the knowledge,
나는 절대 저것은 못할거야,
나는 모델링 소프트웨어를 사용해서
of the modeling software.
저것을 만들 수 있는 지식이 없으니까.
Like I can’t do that.
그러니까 단지 나는 할 수 없을 뿐이란 말이죠.
But when you see Minecraft,
the Minecraft Enterprise,
하지만 마인크래프트 상에,
만들어진 엔터프라이즈 호를 봤다면,
you’re like,
“You couldn’t.”
"당신이 저것을 어떻게?"
라고 생각하겠죠.
Let’s be clear.
좀 명확히 말하자면
Like you could never
do that.
저것은 누구도 못할거야
라고 생각은 하면서
But there’s a part of you
that thinks,
머리 한쪽 구석에서는 당신은
이렇게 생각할 것입니다.
“If I just had the time...”
"글쎄, 나도 시간만 좀 많다면..."
It’s sort of democratized,
right?
그러니까 사실은 아무나 할 수 있습니다.
그렇죠?
Because everybody has
the same pieces.
다들 똑같은 도구가
주어졌으니까요.
And in this you’re making it
out of something.
그리고 그것을 통해서 여러분은
무엇인가 만들어낼 수 있습니다.
And there’s a being in there
that is doing it.
그리고 실제로 그 일들을 하는
사람이 꼭 있다는 말입니다.
Right?
안그런가요?
So, it’s much easier,
I think,
그렇게 말하면 더 쉬울것 같네요.
제 생각에는
to map yourself
to that.
그런 상황에 당신을
대입 한다면 말이죠.
This is Voyager.
이것은 보이져호 입니다.
There’s the Enterprise E.
이것은 엔터프라이즈호 E 입니다.
There is the Klingon Bird-of-Prey.
이것은 클링온 족의 Bird-of-Prey 비행기 입니다.
So, we can make these ships,
take these blocks,
그러니까 우리는 이런 비행기들을
블록들을 가지고
and put them in this world
where we can build our ships...
이 세계에 안에서 공간이 허락되는
만들 수 있습니다.
...with these blocks,
and then, you know,
이 블록들만 있으면,
당신은 말이죠,
wire them up,
give them life,
조합해서 그것들에게
생명력을 불어넣어 줘서
and see what happens.
어떤 일들이 벌어지는지 볼 수 있습니다.
But if you have something take it,
and try going in a completely different direction.
여러분들이 가지고 있는 것들을 통해
기존과 완전히 다른 방향으로 생각을 해 보세요.
Take the seeds of it,
and then see what else you can do.
근본적인 구성 요소들을 가지고
다른 무엇을 할 수 있는지 한번 살펴보는것.
I don’t wanna see bigger
and better,
저는 무엇인가 크고 원래들의 것보다
더 좋은 것을 보고 싶은 것이 아닙니다.
I wanna see this way
or that way.
저는 이런것도 보고 싶고
전혀 다른 것들도 보고 싶습니다.
Hey guys, I just want
to show you a project...
여러분 안녕하세요? 저는 여러분들에게
프로젝트 하나를 보여드리고 싶어요...
...I’ve been working on
in Minecraft.
... 제가 마인크래프트로 작업하고
있는 프로젝트 입니다.
It’s up here.
여기 위에 있습니다.
At least a good view
of it is.
최소한 제가 만든 것에 대한
광경은 확실히 보실 수 있습니다.
This is a Arithmetic-Logic Unit.
이것은 연산 처리 장치 입니다.
And an ALU is found in every processor
because it does math.
연산 처리 장치는 모든 프로세서에 있는데,
수학적 연산을 담당하기 때문이죠.
When the Minecraft
Enterprise came out,
마인크래프트로 만들어진 엔터프라이즈호가
나왔을 때 쯤에,
the computer came out
at about that same time.
마인크래프트로 만들어진 컴퓨터도
그때쯤 나왔습니다.
It is 16-bit,
and somewhat slow,
이것은 16 비트 이고요
조금 느기리고 하고,
and big,
and unwieldy,
크기도 하고,
쉽게 이동 시킬 수도 없습니다.
but it’s implemented
in the video game what do you want?
하지만 이것은 비디오 게임 안에서 구현되었습니다.
무엇을 더 바라십니까?
I have it set up, hopefully,
so that when I add registers,
거의 다 지어진 상태인데, 아마도요,
레지스터를 추가하고,
and ram,
probably not very much ram,
그 전에 많은 용량은 아니지만
램도 추가하고
and program counter,
it will be a legit computer.
프로그램 카운터를 추가 한다면
사용 가능한 컴퓨터가 됩니다.
Okay, so this is the ALU
of a basic computer.
어쨌든, 이것은 연산처리 장치이고요
컴퓨터의 가장 기본이 되는 것입니다.
So, this is the output.
그리고 이것은 아웃풋입니다.
These are the inputs.
이것들은 인풋이고요.
And these are the controls.
그리고 이것들이 컨트롤 입니다.
I’m gonna do 2+1.
제가 지금 2+1을 해보겠습니다.
It’s gonna be crazy.
결과는 굉장히 놀라울 것입니다.
I’m gonna turn that on
so it adds it,
이것을 키면,
덧셈이 이루어 집니다.
and we look over here,
there’s a huge bus...
그리고 이쪽을 보시면,
아주 큰 버스가 있습니다...
...taking all the values
from the end of the ALU,
...값들을 연산처리 장치의
한쪽 끝에서 부터 가지고
all the way back over here.
여기까지 가져오게 하지요.
So, bit wise I mean,
we added 2+1,
그래서, 2+1을
비트 연산으로 했습니다.
we get three,
which is one, one...
그러면 3이 나오고
그 값은 1, 1 에 해당됩니다.
It can only add, really,
but multiplication...
실제로는 덧셈 밖에 하지는 못합니다,
하지만 곱셈은...
is just adding over
and over again.
생각해 보면 덧셈을
여러번 하는 것입니다.
division is subtracting
over and over again,
나눗셈은 뺄셈을
여러번 하는 것이고요,
and subtraction is just
adding a negative number.
뺄셈은 사실 음수를 사용해
덧셈을 하는 것일 뿐입니다.
If pieced together,
they can do any operation
이 사실들을 조합한다면,
이것은 어떤 연산이든 할 수 있습니다.
that a regular computer
can do.
일반적인 컴퓨터가 하는
연산은 모두 말이죠.
Okay, this has four bytes
of memory.
이것은 4 바이트의 메모리를
갖고 있습니다.
I would say in Minecraft
you could probably build...
제 생각에는 만약에 마인크래프트에서
제대로 만든다면 아마도...
...512 bytes of ram.
... 한 512 바이트의 램을 갖도록 만들 수 있습니다.
Which 256 bytes is the amount
that was in an Atari 2600.
아타리 2600은 256 바이트의
램을 가지고 있었죠.
So, that kinda gives you
a feel.
이런 수치들이 여러분들께
어느정도 감을 줄 수 있을겁니다.
So, you could probably
double that.
그러니까 우리는 그 수치의
두배를 설치할 수 있으니까.
So, here’s the entire computer.
그렇게 하면 컴퓨터 하나가 나옵니다.
Here you can see.
여기 보시면요.
You can see the connections,
you can see the cross over.
연결하는 선들을 보실 수 있고,
교차하는 구조도 보실 수 있습니다.
You get a very visceral way
to appreciate what’s going on...
아마도 더이상 컴퓨터 안에서 어떤
일들이 발생하는지 보기 힘들기 때문에
...inside these things
that we can’t see anymore.
자연적으로 이것을 보고는
감탄할 수 밖에 없을겁니다.
There’s not just a disconnect
between regular people,
이 세계와의 단절은 일반
사용자들 뿐만 아니라
even programmers,
just usually taking on faith...
프로그래머들에게서도 볼수 있습니다.
이제는 컴퓨터는 원래
...that they click a button,
and now all this stuff they wrote...
버튼을 클릭하거나,
작업한 코드가
...can be run.
돌아가게 하는것이라 믿는것 같습니다.
That this disconnect can even
translates into people...
이런 단절이 없어야 하는 사람들에게
까지도 이 내용이 전달되어
...who are suppose to know
what’s going on...
컴퓨터 내부에서 어떤 일이 일어나는지
보고 감탄할 수 있다는 것은
...is really interesting.
흥미로운 것 같습니다.
but there’s definitely this class
of machines we have now...
분명히 최근에 나오는
기계들은 성능이
...that are tantamount
to magic,
마술에 가까울 정도로 경이로운
수준에 있기는 하지만,
and we just see them go,
and watch them do...
우리는 그냥 그것이 동작하고
다양한 놀라운 작업을
...all these amazing things,
and nod,
하는 것을 보고 우리는,
고개만 끄떡이면서
and say, “Okay, this is where
we are right now.”
말하죠, "그래, 인류의 기술은
이정도 수준 까지 왔어."
And know that the chain
of us moving from the present...
그리고 우리가 현재로부터
미래로가는 쇠사슬이라는...
...to the future.
...깨닫습니다.
And now there’s gonna be
even cooler things.
그리고 앞으로는 더 멋진
것들이 등장하겠죠.
And that’s just kind of where
it stops,
그리고 언젠가 우리는
멈춰 서서 갑자기
and you don’t say,
“Okay, how does this work?”
"이것이 어떻게 작동 하던 것이었더라?"
라고 질문을 던지지는 않죠.
“What are we really doing?”
"우리가 진짜로 하려고 하는 것이 무엇이지?"
I hope you guys
check in later...
저는 여러분들이 꼭
나중에 이 작품을 다시
...to see this once
I have a few other...
확인해 주셨으면 좋겠네요.
제가 몇가지 더 추가하고
...finished chunks done.
더 완성된 후에 말입니다.
Thanks for watching.
감상해 주셔서 감사합니다.
Infrastructure is such a key part
of Minecraft’s success, I think.
인터넷의 기반시설들이 마인크래프트가
성공하게 된 핵심이라고 저는 생각합니다.
Because it’s a game
about sharing,
왜냐하면 공유를 위한
게임이고
so you just need that infrastructure
in place to share...
공유를 하기 위해서는 그걸을 위한
기반 시설들이 필요하게 됩니다.
...either your creations,
or your things...
공유를 하려고 하는 것이
창작물이든 뭐든 간에...
...that you’ve engineered
in game...
게임에서 만들어낸 것을 말이죠.
...like a color printer
I saw somebody made last week.
제가 저번주에 본 컬러 프린터와
같은 작품들 말입니다.
To share those ideas,
right?
그런 아이디어를 공유하기 위해서는
그렇죠?
Those ideas need places
to move around.
그런 아이디어들이 공유되는
공간이 필요합니다.
Without YouTube,
without Twitter,
YouTube 없이는,
Twitter 없이는
message boards,
community sites,
게시판도 그렇고,
커뮤니티 사이트도 마찬가지고요
it wouldn’t have been
as successful, for sure.
그런것들이 아니었다면, 분명
이렇게 까지는 성공하지 못했을 것입니다.
So, I’m gonna now show you
some pictures of some...
자, 이제 제가 여러분께
사진 몇장을 보여드리겠습니다.
...of the cooler things we found,
and people have built...
사라들이 마인크래프트로 만든 것들
중에 우리가 찾은 멋진...
...in Minecraft.
작품들 입니다.
Whoa, the Eiffel Tower!
우와~ 에펠 탑이다!!!
What?
뭐라고요?
That is so cool!
너무나 멋진걸요!!!
How did they do that?
어떻게 저런 것을 만들까요?
Okay, that’s--
Okay, that is a lot of work.
음, 그래...
음, 잉여력 참 돋네.
That looks pretty cool.
그것 참 간지 돋네요.
I would, like,
never thought of that.
저라면, 저것을
상상도 못했을 것입니다.
Ooh, a castle!
오~ 성이다!!!
Is that Hogwart's?
저것은 호그와트인가요?
It is!
그렇구나!!!
I’m smart!
난 천재야!
No, you’re a nerd!
아니, 넌 괴짜야!!!
It’s self-perpetuating in that way
of because people create things,
스스로 자생할 수 있는 환경이 구축된
것은 사람들이 무엇인가 창조해 내고
and they spend time
creating things.
창조해 내는데 시간을
많이 투자하기 때문입니다.
They wanna share
those things.
그들은 그것들을
공유하고 싶어 하죠.
So, automatically more people,
and new people are hearing...
그래서 자동적으로 더 많은 사람들이
그 게임에 대해 다양한 맥락을 통해서...
...about that game
in a contextual way.
게임에 대해 듣게 됩니다.
They’re not watching an ad,
they’re saying,
그들은 어떤 광고를 보는 것이
아니고, 공유한 것을 통해 사람들은
“Hey, I made this.”
"여러분, 제가 이것을 만들었어."
“You can do this too!”
"여러분도 할 수 있습니다!"
“Do you wanna play?”
"여러분도 해보실래요?"
I found out through,
was it Tyco's post...
제가 알게된 것은
Penny Arcade에 올라온
...on Penny Arcade?
Tyco의 게시물을 통해서였나요?
I’m not sure,
but I heard about it there,
확실히 기억은 안나네요,
하지만 그곳에서 접하게 되었습니다.
and my best friend was like,
“Hey, it’s a game where all you do...
그런데 제 친구가 그러더군요,
"야, 그 게임에서 하는 것이라고는...
...is mine and craft.”
...광물 캐고 뭔가 만드는일 뿐이야"
And I was like,
“Really now?”
그 얘기를 듣고 저는 이랬습니다.
"진짜란 말이지?"
I definitely wanted to
spread the word too, like.
이 얘기를 듣고 저는 너무나
이 소식을 사람들에게 알려주고 싶었습니다.
Yeah, there was an evangelical,
sort of.
그러니까 그 소식이 저에게 뭔가
전도에 대한 열의를 심어줬다고나 할까요?
It was at the very beginning
of the--
거의 초창기때의 일인데
-The big, like--
-The take off of the game, right?
-그러니까 크게...
-게임이 대박나기 전에요, 그렇죠?
-Yeah.
-So there wasn’t a lot...
-맞아요.
-그래서 그 게임을 한다는 것이
of material out there
about what it was like...
어떤 느낌인지에 대한
그런 정보가 많이...
...to actually play it.
...존재 하지 않았습니다.
Like this game will suck
you in,
예를 들어 이 게임은 당신을
흡수할 것이니까
and you are in trouble.
당신은 이제 큰일이라는 말 같은 정보요.
And then you introduced
your son to it,
그런데 게임을 당신 아들에게
소개를 해 주었죠,
and every time I would go over
to your house,
그 이후로 제가 당신 집에
놀러 갈 때 마다
he was playing it
the entire time.
아들이 그 게임을
항상 하고 있더라고요.
Yeah, still is.
그래요, 아직도 그렇답니다.
Hours.
몇 시간씩이요.
Every night,
hours.
매일 밤,
몇 시간씩요.
Hot.
아주 열정적이에요.
I pictured him sorta getting in there,
and not knowing what to do.
저는 녀석이 게임을 시작하고서는 무엇 부터
어떻게 해야 할지 모를것이라 생각했습니다.
It turns out that wasn’t
an issue.
하지만 결과적으로는
기우였습니다.
So, where’s you’re, uh,
don’t you have...
그래서, 그거 어디있더라,
뭔가 있었던것 같은데...
...a train station
in here somewhere?
기차역 같은 것이 여기
있지 않았니?
Oh wow,
that’s cool.
오 와우,
그것 참 멋있구나.
I saw the one that--
they had a bunch of music blocks,
제가 본 것 중에는 뮤직 블록이
엄청 많이 있어서
and it played the song
from Portal.
Portal에 나오는 음악을
연주하는 것도 있었어요.
He’s my boy.
제 아들입니다.
I love you son.
사랑한다 아들아.
What?
어째서요?
-What?
-Oh nothing.
-제가 뭘 했죠?
-아무것도 아니란다.
You know, it’s interesting,
because especially as a parent,
부모의 입장에서 굉장히
흥미롭다는 것을 아십니까?
you think, “Boy, I really need
to limit--”
"이젠 정말 애가 게임 하는 것을 제한 해야겠어"
하고 생각하시겠지만,
You just hear you have
to limit his time--
어디선가 그렇게 해야 한다고
들어서 그런것은 아닌가요?
You have to limit their time
in video games.
부모로써 애들이 게임하는 것을
제한해야 한다고 보통 그러잖아요.
You don’t really know why,
and I think that’s...
그런데 사실 왜 그래야 하는지
우리는 잘 모르고요, 제가 보기에는
...I think that’s just ridiculous now,
because you know,
...이제는 터무니 없는 말이라고 생각합니다.
왜냐하면 생각해 보면,
what is a video game anymore?
더이상 비디오 게임이 뭐라고 생각하십니까?
When he’s been playing
for a couple of hours,
제 애가 2시간 정도
게임을 했을 때에
and I come in,
and I’m like,
제가 방에 들어가서
이렇게 말합니다.
“Alright, Gabe, I think
you need to take a break.”
"게이브야, 이제 좀 쉴
때가 된것 같구나."
And I look,
and he’s built a functioning aqueduct.
하고 보면, 아들이 정상 작동하는
송수로를 만들어 놓습니다.
That’s no joke.
장난 아닙니다.
Like he figured out
how to get water...
그러니까 말하자면, 스스로
물을 어떤식으로 한곳에서...
...from one place to another
by building this contrap--
...다른 곳으로 이동 시킬 수 있는지
기계를 만들어서 알아냈습니다.
It’s like I’m not gonna tell you
to stop.
그런데 제가 그만 하라고
하겠습니까?
You know?
Parenting has changed.
그러니까, 말하자면
아이 양육법은 이제 바뀌었습니다.
We have, uh,
these nice people.
오늘은 좋은 분들이
우리를 방문해 주셨어요.
They’re from a real
film company...
진짜 영화제작사에서
오신 분들인데...
...making a real movie
about Minecraft.
...지금 마인크래프에 관한
진짜 영화를 제작중이에요.
And they’re just gonna be watching
what we do.
그분들이 오늘 우리가 무엇을 하는지
살펴보시기로 했어요.
We’re gonna be doing
what we normally do.
우리는 우리가 평소에 하던
그대로 하면 됩니다.
We’re gonna be
playing Minecraft.
우리는 오늘 마인크래프트를
즐길 것입니다.
I’m gonna be--
have activities for you.
제가 여러분들을 위해
준비한 활동이 있습니다.
You guys are gonna get
to do your own things.
여러분은 여러분들이
하고 싶은 것을 하면 됩니다.
But really just,
we’re gonna be ourselves today.
그런데 제일 중요한 것은,
우리가 우리의 평소 모습을 보여주는 것입니다.
Kyle, yes.
네, Kyle 학생.
I have always been
a gamer.
저는 평생 게이머로
살았습니다.
I still remember the day
my cousin brought over...
저는 아직도 사촌형이
저희 집에 Pong 게임기를
...a Pong machine,
and that was sort of...
가지고 왔던 날을 잊을 수 없습니다.
그 날은 제 인생을 바꿔놓은
...like a life-changing moment,
and I kinda grew up...
날 중에 하나가 되었고,
저는 컴퓨터 게임들과 함께
...with computer games
in my life.
성장하는 인생을
살게 되었습니다.
Right now, I’m teaching
our Lower School Technology classes.
저는 지금 저학년에게
기술을 가르치고 있습니다.
So, I’m mostly working
with first and second grade,
그래서 보통 1~2학년
학생들과 생활하고 있는데,
and I’m a big believer that
in bringing games into the classroom.
저는 교실에 게임을 도입해야 한다고
믿는 사람 중에 한 사람 입니다.
I think it gets the kids really excited
about being here,
저는 게임덕에 애들이 여기에 와 있다는
사실에 흥분한다고 생각합니다.
being in school,
being in my class.
학교에 있다는것,
교실에 있다는것 말 입니다.
Do you like school?
학교 다니는게 좋나요?
Sometimes.
때때로요
Well, what's your favorite--
do you like the Minecraft stuff?
그럼, 어떤 수업이 좋아요?
마인크래프트로 하는 것도 좋아요?
Yeah, computer is
my favorite subject.
네, 컴퓨터가 제가 제일
좋아하는 과목이에요.
Kids are excited
about games.
애들은 게임 때문에
흥분합니다.
This is where they live.
그곳이 그들이 생활하는 공간입니다.
You know, they go home,
they play games,
그들이 집에 가면
게임을 즐긴다는것 아시잖아요.
that’s what they’re excited
to talk about with their friends.
그것이 바로 애들이 친구들이랑
대화할때 가장 흥분하는 주제입니다.
It’s this generation.
그냥 이 세대가 그렇습니다.
You have a computer,
or a Wii?
집에 컴퓨터나
Wii(닌텐도 위)가 있나요?
Yeah, we have
a Wii,
네, 저희 집에는요,
Wii도 있고요,
an XBOX,
A PS3.
XBOX도 있고요,
PS3도 있어요.
My older brother
has a PlayStation.
제 형이 PlayStation을
가지고 있어요.
And they’re talking about
doing well in a class,
학교에서 공부를 잘 하려면
어떻게 해야하는지에 대해 이야기 하고,
and leveling up.
또 레벨을 올릴 수 있는지 이야기 합니다.
I mean this is where
they live.
이곳이 그들이 사는 공간입니다.
This is kind of where
their mental head space is.
이곳이 그들의 정신세계가<br? 존재하는 곳입니다.
And when I started playing Minecraft
this past summer,
제가 지난 여름에 마인크래프트를
처음 해봤을 때 말이죠,
I just, you know,
there was just such...
그때, 뭐라고 해야 할까요,
정말 굉장히...
...amazing amounts of potential
that I really knew...
...엄청난 잠재력이 있다고
생각하고, 이것을...
...that I had to try
to make it work,
...교실로 들여오는 것을 시도하고
꼭 성공할 수 있는 방법을
and find a way to bring this
into my classroom.
찾아봐야 겠다는 생각을
했습니다.
I’m gonna break you guys
into groups.
저는 이제 여러분을
여러개의 조로 나눌거에요
And each group is gonna
make their own house...
각 조는 자신들만의 집을
다양한 재료를 사용해서...
...out of these different materials.
...자신들만의 집을 만들어야 합니다.
Max is off and running
making some tools.
Max는 도구를 만들기 위해
여기저기 뛰어다니고 있네.
Guys, I’ll make doors
for us.
얘들아, 내가 우리 집에
사용할 문짝을 만들게
-In the desert.
-Oh, I see it.
-저기 사막에.
-아, 나도 보인다.
You got it.
바로 그거야.
You guys like the game?
너희들은 이 게임이 좋니?
Yeah.
네
It is really,
really fun.
이 게임은 진짜로,
진짜로 재미 있어요.
Like, it’s kinda like
a free world.
그러니까, 내 마음대로 할 수 있는
자유의 세계니까요.
It’s not like New York City
with all the traffic,
뉴욕시 처럼 엄청난 교통량이
있는 것도 아니고,
and all,
I love it.
여러가지 면에서 저는
이 게임을 사랑합니다.
I’m able to dream up
these different worlds,
저는 이제 아이들이 경험할
수 있는 다양한 세상과 모험들에 대해
and different adventures
that the kids can have...
꿈을 꿔 봅니다.
저는 아이들이...
...that I think they’re gonna
get something out of.
...그 경험으로부터 무엇인가
얻어가는 것이 있으리라 생각합니다.
That they’re gonna have--
that’s gonna have...
그들에게 평생 사는 동안
오래오래 간직할 수 있는...
...some lasting value for them.
...의미 있는 가치가 될만한 것을요.
Well, Minecraft is basically
another version of your life,
그러니까, 마인크래프트는 쉽게 말해서
당신의 인생의 또 다른 버전입니다,
except it’s a magical version.
다만 마법의 버전일 뿐이죠.
Lots of great team work today.
오늘 여러분 협동심은 굉장했어요.
And I had a lot of positive feedback.
그리고 저는 굉장히 긍정적인 피드백을 많이 받았습니다.
You know, our network administrator
told me really early on...
우리 네트워크 관리자는 예전에
제게 이런 말을 했는데...
...this is one of the coolest
things I’ve ever seen done...
...제가 하고 있는 것이 자기가 이 학교에
와서 일한 긴 세월 동안 이러난 일 가운데...
...in all the years of working
in schools.
...가장 멋진 일이라고
했습니다.
Then the teachers who
are not gamers,
그리고, 게임을 하지 않는
선생님들도 말이죠.
yeah, I mean,
I guess they would kind of...
그러니까 그들은,
아직은 상황에 익숙하지 않아서...
...scratch their heads,
and they’d say that’s nice, Joel.
...어리둥절하게 머리를 긁으면서,
그저 제가 잘하고 있는것 같다고 말해주겠죠.
You know, I’m glad you’re doing
something fun with the kids.
그저 제가 아이들과 즐거운 시간을
보내고 있으니 다행이라고 할 겁니다.
But, once I would get them
in the room for five minutes,
하지만 제가 그 분들을 방으로
5분만이라도 모셔올 수 있어서
once they would see
just how excited,
아이들이 얼마나 신나
하는지 살펴보고
and how engaged
the kids were,
아이들이 얼마나 수업에
참여하는지 살펴 보게 된다면
you know, almost everyone
of these teachers...
이 선생님들의 대부분이
그러니까...
...would walk out of the room
a believer...
...이 방을 걸어나가
제가 믿는 것 처럼...
...that I was really
on to something here.
...게임을 교실로 들여야 한다고
믿게 될 것입니다.
Not sure I fully
understand it.
제가 이것을 잘 이해하고
있는지 모르겠네요.
I’m not sure I understand it at all,
to be honest with you.
솔직히 말해서 조금이라도 제대로 이해하고
있는지도 잘 모르겠습니다.
When I first saw this game,
I thought,
제가 이 게임을 처음 봤을때,
생각했습니다.
“Wow, this is really pixelly,
and this reminds me...
"와우, 이것 참 그림이 사각지고,
내가 Atari 800을 즐기던...
...of my Atari 800 days.”
...시절이 떠오르게 하는구나."
And I couldn’t believe that the kids
were satisfied with the graphics.
그래서 아이들이 이정도 그래픽에
만족한다는 사실이 믿어지지 않았습니다.
But they don’t even seem
to notice that part of it.
하지만, 아이들이 그 부분에 대해서는
전혀 신경을 안쓰는것 같았습니다.
Do you like playing Minecraft?
마인크래프트 하는거 재미있어요?
It’s awesome!
완전 짱이에요!
It’s so much fun.
하는것이 너무나 즐거워요.
That’s the only part
I don’t like.
그거 하나에 대해서만
싫어해요.
Listening to everyone
talk about it all the time.
사람들이 항상 그것에 대해서
이야기 하는 것을 들어야 한다는것이요.
The kids come in,
and you literally...
아이들이 일단 들어오면,
말 그대로 아이들을...
...have to rip their hands
off of the keyboard.
키보드에 붙어있는 손을
뜯어서 떼어 버려야 합니다.
You don't like listening to everyone
talk about it all the time?
It’s annoying.
좀 거슬려요.
And I love to talk
about it.
하지만 저는 그것에 대해
이야기 하는 것을 너무 좋아해요.
You two still manage to get along...
even though he talks about Minecraft all the time?
-No.
-Yeah.
-아니요
-네
But let’s remember
there’s things they can do...
우리는 마인크래프트에서
할 수 있는 일과 현실 세계에서는
...in Minecraft that they can’t
do in the real world.
절대 하지 못하는 일이 있음을
기억해야 합니다.
I mean, I can’t drop a bunch of kids
in a forest,
제 말은, 현실 세계에서는 우리 아이들을
숲 속에 내버려 두고서는
and tell them to build
a shelter in real life.
피난 처를 알아서 만들라고 할 수는
없지 않습니까?
And even if it’s not quite
real life,
그리고 아주 현실적인 세계가
아니라 하더도
they’re thinking,
“Well, what would I do...
아이들이 이렇게 생각하지 않을까요?
"글쎄, 여기 이 상황에서 내가...
...in this situation?”
...무엇을 해야 하지?"
What must it be like to build
a castle on top...
산 꼭대기 위에 성을
짓고 요새로 만드는...
...of the mountain,
and try to fortify it.
...것을 시도하는 것은 과연
어떤 기분일까요.
What must it be like
to explore a jungle.
정글을 탐험한다는 것은
과연 어떤 기분일까요.
What must it be like
to farm,
농장을 짓고 작물을
키운다는 것은
and raise crops.
과연 어떤 기분일까요.
I mean, these are things
they can do in the game.
제 말은 이것들은 모두
게임에서는 가능한 일이라는 것입니다.
And then if a teacher is able
to spend a little time customizing it,
만약 선생님이 시간을 조금 투자해서
원하는 형태로 미리 이런 시나리오들을
setting up these scenarios,
the potential is limitless.
구성해 놓을 수 있다면,
여기서 얻을 수 있는 잠재력은 무한합니다.
Well, with the teaching,
we’re gonna go talk to...
그리고 가르치는 것에 관해서는
우리는 뉴욕에 계시는...
...the Minecraft teacher
in New York. ...마인크래프트 선생님을 방문해
이야기를 해보도록 할 것입니다.
Okay.
알겠습니다.
And we’ll see him teaching classes,
and things like that.
그 분께서 수업을 어떻게 진행하는지
한번 살펴보고 그럴 겁니다.
I mean is that something
you ever expected...
혹시 이런 현상들이
덩달아 발생할 것이라고...
...would come with the game?
...생각 하셨나요?
No.
아니요.
I think his nickname is “Notch”.
제가 알기로는 그 분의 닉네임이
Notch인 것으로 알고 있는데요.
Oh yeah, “Notch”.
네 맞아요, Notch요.
Nacho,
you’re a great man!
Nacho님,
당신은 위대합니다!
“Notch”.
Notch라니까.
I think the person
would be very smart...
제 생각에는 엄청 똑똑한
사람이니까요...
...to make Minecraft.
...마인크래프트 같은 것을 마들 수 있지 않았을까요?
I think he likes adventures.
그 분은 모험을 좋아하는것 같아요.
I actually look forward
to 15 years from now...
저는 사실 지금으로부터 15년
후를 바라보며 기대하고 있습니다.
...when these kids--
well, not my age necessarily,
그러니까 애들이--
꼭 제 나이 또래가 될 필요는 없고요,
I’m a bit older than that,
but when they’re grown up,
저는 좀 나이가 있으니까,
어쨌든, 애들이 성인이 되어
and to have a conversation
with someone...
제가 그들 중에 누군가와
대화를 나누게 된다면
...it’s like,
“What, you worked on Minecraft?”
그러니까 이렇게 질문한다면
"뭐라고요? 당신이 마인크래프트를 만들었어요?"
Well not really,
but I sat next to the guy who did.
엄밀히 말하자면 만든 사람
옆에 앉아 있었지
Because I’ve--
just like you’re saying,
왜냐하면 저는--
이미 말씀하신 것과 같이,
some of the games,
you played when you were young,
유년 시절에 즐기던
게임들은 말이에요
just, they stick with you.
평생 당신의 머릿속에 박히게 됩니다.
And it’s gonna be that
over Minecraft as well.
마인크래프트도 마찬가지로
그렇게 될 것입니다.
It’s gonna be awesome to hear that
in 15, 20 years talking to people.
15~20년 후에 사람들이 그런식으로
이야기하게 된다면 정말 멋질 것입니다.
And it’s also gonna be very fun
to see what Minecraft means...
그 시점에 마인크래프트가 무엇을
의미 하는지 보게 된다는 것은...
...at that point, so.
즐거운 일일 것입니다.
I’m very much looking forward
to that.
저는 그런 미래를 바라보며
기대하고 있습니다.
It’s gonna be interesting,
because they’re gonna...
그렇게 된다면 흥미로울 것입니다.
왜냐하면 사람들이...
...be looking back on it
nostalgically...
...자신들의 과거를 향수에
젖어서 회고하게 될테니까요.
in like ten years
from now.
지금으로 부터 한
10년 후에는 말이죠.
Ah, that’s a scary thought.
아, 정말 부담스러운 생각이네요.
Yeah, that means,
yeah.
네, 그 말은,
그러니까.
That means we really need
to do it right.
그 말은 일을 정말 제대로
해야 한다는 말이겠네요.
We have so much to do,
and not much time...
우리는 할일이 참 많은데
시간이 많지 않네요...
...until the release date.
...릴리스하기로 한 그 날까지요.
And I was kind of joking
that the release date...
아니 그런데 사실 릴리스 날짜에
대한 말은 농담입니다.
...that we’re told is not
really a release date,
릴리스 날짜라고 명확히
말하지는 않았고요,
it’s like, well,
it’s more like an aim.
그러니까, 목표일에
더 가깝습니다.
But Carl didn’t agree.
하지만 Carl은 동의하지 않았죠.
He said, “It’s going to be released
that day regardless.”
그는 "일이 어떻게 되든지간데 그 날에
릴리스를 해야 해"라고 말했죠.
My attempt to push it
a little failed.
너무 무리하지 말자는 주장을 관철
시키기 위한 제 작은 노력은 실패 했습니다.
Hey.
어이.
What's up, sir?
네, 무슨 일이십니까?
How's it going?
일이 어떻게 진행되고 있나요?
Good.
잘 되고 있어요.
Carl, you look like a rock star, man. Geez.
Carl, 지금 록 스타 같아요. 쩌는데요.
I don't feel like one.
나는 그렇게 느껴지지 않아요.
It's going good.
잘 진행 되고 있어요
I'm a bit stressed out.
저는 지금 약간 스트레스 받아 지쳐있어요.
Definite--the pressure
is increasing in the team.
절대적으로 팀이 느끼고 있는
부담은 커지고 있습니다.
I would say I need to finish this,
so I'm really focused on it,
저는 지금 이 일을 끝내야 해서,
정말로 이 일에만 집중하고 있어서
so right now it doesn't feel like
we'll ever work on something new,
지금 당장은 앞으로 평생동안 새로운
것에는 손도 못댈 것 같은 심정이네요.
but I have all these
ideas that I want to try.
하지만 시도해 보고 싶은
아이디어들은 많아요.
And I've actually like spoken to Jens
and he would be willing to take over...
그리고 실제로 Jens랑 이야기도 해봤는데
그가 이 일을 이어받아 할 의지가 있더군요.
...like the head of Minecraft
and he's really good at it.
그러니까 마인크래프트 책임자 말이죠.
그는 정말 능력이 있거든요.
So, I feel comfortable that he's someone
who could do a very good job at it,
그가 일을 잘 해낼 수 있다는 것을 알고
있게 때문에 마음이 편하지만
but right now it feels like I'm gonna
keep working on Minecraft forever.
하지만 지금 느낌으로는 제가 평생
마인크래프트에 매달려야 할것 같네요.
We'll see.
어디 한번 봐야 할것 같습니다.
I'm very excited about it being done
because it's like a milestone, I think,
이 일이 끝나는 것에 대해 잔뜩 흥분되어 있습니다.
아마도 우리끼리 자축할 만한 중요한
that would be really worth celebrating.
중요한 단계가 될 것 같거든요.
Like, "Yeah, now you've made
it, this game, now it's finished."
그러니까 "그래, 당신이 만들기 시작한 게임이
이제는 완성 되었어."라는 느낌
So, yeah, I don't
think it's sad like that.
하지만, 뭔가 슬픈 일이
될 것 같지는 않아요.
I mean, maybe, you know, I don't know how
long this game will live and be popular,
제 말은, 이 게임이 얼마나 오랫동안
유명세를 떨칠지는 모르겠지만
but maybe when it fades,
then you would feel a bit sad like,
만약 인기가 식는다면
그 사실이 약간 슬프게 하겠지만
"Oh, yeah,"
I'd be nostalgic.
"아, 그땐 그랬지"
하며 향수에 젖을 수 있겠죠.
You know like, "Oh, I remember when
it was so popular," you know.
그러니까 이런식으로요,
"아, 아주 인기가 많았을 때가 생각나"
But, no, it definitely
doesn't feel like that.
하지만 지금 당장은
그렇게 느껴지지는 않을거에요.
I think it will keep
gaining, so.
제 생각에는 인기를
계속 끌 것 같아요.
Oh yeah, another bug, the bow doesn't
get damaged when you use it.
아 맞아, 또 하나의 버그가 있어. 활이
사용해도 마모가 안되더라고요.
We're just taking today
as a final, like, polish day.
우리는 오늘 일을 마무리 짓고
정리하는 날로 정했습니다.
We have a few reported crash bugs that
we can't reproduce, so it's like,
보고된 버그 중에 지금 재현하지
못하는 것이 몇가지 있지만,
we would like to fix them,
but we don't know how.
고치고 싶어도 어떻게 할 수
있는지 지금은 모르겠습니다.
Yeah.
네.
I'm a bit nervous because, mostly because
there are gonna be, hopefully reviews,
지금 약간 긴장되는데, 가장 큰
이유는 분명히 후기들이 올라오거든요.
and those are gonna give the game
like a score and they're gonna say,
그러면 그 후기들이 곧 이 게임에 대한
점수이고 사람들은 말할 것입니다.
"No, this game is five percent less good
than the Super Mario Galaxy" or something.
"이 게임은 슈퍼마리오 갤럭시 보다 5%
부족하군" 같은 말 말입니다.
Like here's a bug.
보세요, 여기도 버그가 있잖아요.
"Redstone torch randomly
burn out and never recover."
"붉은 돌 횃불 무작위로
타버리고 재생되지 않음."
Okay, where do I start?
그래서, 어디서 부터 시작하죠?
I have no idea, so.
글쎄요, 나도 잘 모르겠네요.
Oh, so fun this is.
아, 정말 신나는 일이군.
Oh, there we go.
자, 이제 된다.
Now that's right, correct.
이제 정상적으로 제대로 작동하는군.
Oh, damn it.
아, 젠장.
I'll mark this as
can't reproduce.
이건 그냥 재현할 수 없는
없는 것으로 표시해야겠다.
So you said you just
sent the game off?
이제 막 게임에 대한
작업을 끝냈나요?
Yeah, I put it on the USB sticks and then
I sent the final like zip file to Tobias,
네, USB 메모리에 넣어두고 죄종 버전을
Tobias에게 압축해서 보내서,
so he can make
the upload script.
그가 업로드 스크립트를
만들 수 있게 했습니다.
Now it's 20 minutes past 3
and I have one-and-a-half days to go...
이제 3시20분인데, 저는 이제
Minecon에 가기 전까지...
...and then we go to Minecon.
...하루하고 반이라는 시간이 있군요.
So I figured I'd
play with Legos.
그래서 저는 레고를
가지고 놀기로 했습니다.
It's a bit weird 'cause
I still feel like I probably
좀 기분이 이상하네요. 왜냐하면
지금 아직도 저는 아마도
should still be polishing stuff
'cause there's stuff to polish,
계속 마무리하는 작업을 해야 할것 같은데,
마무리 지어야할 것들이 있었으니까요.
but I don't want to risk getting new bugs,
so we're not doing that.
하지만 저는 새로운 버그들을 만들어내는 위험을
감수하고 싶지 않아요. 그래서 아무것도 안하는 것입니다.
And I'm super nervous about the flight,
not nervous, more like giddy or something,
처녀 비행을 앞두고 굉장히 긴장되는데,
아니 긴장되는 것을 넘어 어지러울 지경이네요.
like I can't wait
until the flight goes.
비행을 시작하기 까지의
순간이 기다려지네요.
See you guys tomorrow.
여러분 내일 봐요.
Yup, see you then.
네, 그럼 내일 봐요.
So, I think he feels that,
okay I can't do anything more now,
그래요, 그가 어떤 느낌인지 알겠지만
지금으로써는 제가 할 수 있는 일이 없네요.
it's done and
I'm going to Vegas.
이미 엎질러진 물이고
저는 베가스로 갑니다.
So, I think that's why
he's giddy and, uh,
아마도 그래서 어지러운것
같아요. 그리고,
and I started to feel that as well,
so probably tomorrow.
저도 똑같은 느낌이 들기 시작했는데요,
아마도 내일 때문에 그런것 같습니다.
I'm gonna lock down the Scrolls
version tomorrow morning...
내일 아침에는 개발중인 Scrolls의
버전을 잠시 중단하고서...
...and then I'm gonna just kick back
and put my feet up and play some...
...발뻗고 누워서 발을
어딘가에 올려놓고서...
...Virtua Tennis 4 and go out
and have a beer with Markus,
...버츄얼 테니스 4를 조금 하다가
Markus와 함께 술이나 한잘 할것입니다.
and you know, just cool down
before the trip to Vegas.
그리고서 잠시 베가스로 가기
전에 휴식이나 취할것입니다.
It took a whole truck.
트럭 한대 전체가 필요했어.
It's very cool.
정말 멋지네요.
I mean, there's been talk
about 5,000 people.
5,000명 정도의 사람이
있을거라는 말이 있었습니다.
I don't think there's gonna
be that many, but who knows.
제가 보기에는 그만큼 사람이
많지는 않을 것 같은데 또 모르죠.
Yes.
네
It doesn't work at all.
아무것도 안보이네요.
But, uh, we only have
a few more minutes left,
우리에게 아직 몇분 밖에
시간이 남지 않았지만
so we really do want to thank
all of y'all for coming here,
저희는 이곳에 오신 여러분들에게
감사의 말을 전해드리고 싶습니다.
and this has been the highlight
for us of this past year...
오늘이 저희들에게는 지난 1년간의
시간 동안 가장 절정인것 같고요...
...and what Minecraft
has done for all of us.
...마찬가지로 마인크래프트가 우리를 위해
해준 것도 절정에 이르게 된것 같습니다.
Because Minecon is finally
released, it's the end times.
마인콘이 마침내 릴리스 되었으니
이제 일이 성취 되었네요.
No one thought it
would ever happen.
아무도 실제로 이 일이
일어나리라 생각 못했을 것입니다.
It's Minecon--sorry,
it's Minecraft.
마인콘, 아니 죄송합니다.
마인크래프트죠.
That's okay.
괜찮습니다.
I'm getting all of
your games wrong.
제가 당신의 게임들
이름을 다 틀리게 말하고 있군요.
I've played it
a few times.
저도 몇번 해봤습니다.
I heard you did, yeah.
네, 그러셨다고 들었습니다.
Yeah.
네
He's still learning.
아직 배우고 계십니다.
Yeah.
그래요
I guess just to close out,
I think you're obviously idolized...
이제 마무리 할까 하는 의미에서요,
제가 보기에는 당신이 명백히...
...by a lot of, uh--I'm sure
that must make you feel...
...우상화 되고 계신데요, 제가
확신하는데 지금 느낌이 때로는...
...kind of weird at times,
but you're obviously idolized...
...조금 이상하실 겁니다.
하지만 게임을 만들고 싶어하는...
...by a lot of indie developers
and people that want to make games.
...많은 인디 개발자들의 명백한
우상이 되셨습니다.
You know, they look at what you've
done as a kind of success story,
그러니까, 그들은 당신이 이룬
일을 성공신화로 보고,
you know, like you went from being
a guy making an indie game...
그러니까, 인디 게임을 개발하는
한 사람에서 지금은...
...to a guy that can have 5,000 people
come out to a convention to see him.
...이제는 단지 당신을 보기 위해 행사장에
5,000명의 사람이 모이는 그런 사람이 되었는데,
So, do you have any words of advice
to people out there that are,
혹시 인디 개발자가 되고 싶어 하는
이 세상에 있는 많은 사람들에게
you know, trying to become,
you know, an indie developer?
혹시나 해주고 싶은 조언이나
충고가 있습니까?
I think that the best advice
I can give everyone is,
제가 생각하기에 제가 모두에게
줄 수 있는 최고의 조언은
"Don't listen to advice,"
but if you are going to listen to advice,
"다른 사람들의 조언을 듣지 말라"입니다.
하지만 조언을 듣기를 원한다면,
then making sure you actually
do something is good advice.
무엇인가 확실히 해야 한다는
것이 좋은 조언이 될 것 같습니다.
If you just sit around planning
something and not doing it,
그저 앉아서 계획만 짜고 계획을
가지고 아무것도 하지 않을 것이라면
you're not actually
gonna get anywhere.
사실상 아무것도 이루지
못하게 됩니다.
Cool, yeah, I think
that's a good.
멋지십니다. 제가 생각하기에도
좋은 조언 같네요.
-Yeah, cool.
-Are we good?
-정말 좋네요.
-이제 끝났나요?
-Yup.
-Great. Awesome.
-네
-잘됐네요. 수고하셨습니다.
I'm actually not doing
anything myself,
제가 직접 하는 것은
아무것도 없습니다만,
but maybe I fall on
the stairs or something.
혹시라도 계단에서 넘어지거나
그러기라도 하면 어떨까요.
Music please for entry.
시작할때 음악좀 넣어주세요.
This is how it's gonna look--what it's
gonna look like when people are entering.
지금 이것이 사람들이 입장할때
보게될 광경입니다.
So they'll be the music on,
the lights will be low like this.
그러면 음악도 나오고 조명도
지금처럼 은은할 겁니다.
That's impressive.
인상적이네요.
-He's like a magician.
-That's so Las Vegas.
-그는 마법사 같네요.
-완전 라스베가스 같아요.
Everything's gonna get
dark for the HAT Films video.
HAT 필름즈 영상 때는
모든 불이 꺼질겁니다.
It's kind of like how I said how I feel
the game deserves a six or a seven.
제가 말했듯이 제 게임이 6이나 7점 정도로
평가될 것 같은 느낌이 듭니다.
I do realize it's probably going
to get higher scores than that,
아마도 그것 보다는 높은 점수를
받을 수도 있겠지만,
but I don't really dare hope
for that 'cause to me it's a--
감히 그것을 꼭 바라는 것은
아닌데, 그 이유는 말이죠
There's so much more that
could be done to the game.
이 게임에 더 추가될 수 있는
것들이 너무마 낳기 때문입니다.
It's not really finished yet and I
don't think it's ever going to be.
아직은 정말 미완성이고, 제 생각에는
평생 완성 될 일은 없을 것 같아요.
Yeah, it sounds like
the closing ceremony started.
네, 폐막 행사가 지금
막 시작한 것 처럼 들리네요.
Yeah.
좋네요.
Well, would you like
to hear him talk?
자, 이제 이분의 말씀을
들어보고 싶으신가요?
Yeah!
네!
Okay, so, Notch, how does
this feel to you right now?
자, 그러면, Notch씨, 지금
이 상황에 당신에게 어떻게 느껴지나요?
No pressure, yeah.
그럼 편하게 이야기 해보겠습니다, 네.
It's very overwhelming.
너무나 벅찹니다.
I mean, the reason I started working
on Minecraft and kept working on it...
그러니까, 제가 마인크래프트 작업을
계속 유지 했던 이유는...
...was because of people playing it
and it's the reason we started a company...
...사람들이 계속 즐겼기 때문이고,
그래서 회사도 시작하기도 했는데...
...because there were fans, and now
we have like 5,000 people here just for...
...그것도 팬들 때문이었습니다.
그런데 지금 여기 단지 그 게임 하나로...
...the game, for
Minecraft, and that's...
...5,000여명의 사람들을 불러
모을 수 있게 되었는데요 그것은...
We are so thankful that you guys traveled
from all over, literally, the world.
우리는 정말 전 세계 각국에서 이곳까지
방문해 주신 여러분들께 감사드립니다.
We have people from all different
countries here celebrating with us...
여기에는 정말 많은 나라에서
우리와 같이 기념하고...
...to be part of the official release
and we are so grateful...
...공식 릴리스에 동참하기 위해
와준 것에 대해 아주 고맙게 생각하고 있고...
...and absolutely humbled
that you would come all this way...
...그동안 우리 팀의 작업을 보기
위해 여기까지 와주셨다는 것이...
...for this game that this team
has been working on,
...더욱 겸손한 자세로 임해야겠다는
생각이 들게 하기도 합니다.
but now, for the moment that
you have all been waiting for.
어쨌든, 지금으로써는 여러분이
고대하던 것이 나왔습니다.
Yeah, 2011 was probably
the weirdest year of my life.
그렇습니다, 2011년은 아마도
제 인생중에 가장 특이했던 해 같습니다.
It's a--feels like a blur now
that I think back on it.
그러니까, 이제와서 뒤를 돌아보면
정신없이 살아온 것 같습니다.
So much happened and so
I can't even describe it.
너무도 많은 일들이 일어나서
일일히 나열하지도 못하겠네요.
The weirdest year
of my life.
제 인생에 있어서 가장
인상 깊었던 한해였습니다.
It's really hard,
this summing up things.
그동안 일어난 일을 요약하는 것은
매우 어려운 일일 것 같습니다.
You know, it's--'cause there's
so much that has happened...
아시잖아요, 왜냐하면 그동안
너무나 많은 일들이 발생했고...
...and at the same time trying to work and then
of course manage the family back home.
...동시에 일도 하고, 우리 가족을
모두 집까지 귀환 시켜야 했으니까요.
And we had some illness
in the family as well,
그리고 가족원 중에
환자도 있어서,
we're trying to balance that and it's just,
it was almost too much in one year...
모든 것이 잘 돌아가게 신경 쓸 것이 많았는데,
일년에 일어난 것 치고는 많은 일이었던것 같아요.
...I have to say.
제게는 그랬습니다.
Let me show
you around.
여기를 한번 구경
시켜 드리겠습니다.
Watch out.
조심하세요.
Let's see.
어디 봅시다.
Yeah, right as we enter, this is where,
sort of, everyone will sit and work.
네, 여기 들어오자 마자 있는 이 공간은
사람들이 앉아서 일하는 공간이 될 것 같고요.
A bar will be over there.
저기에는 바가 들어올 것입니다.
Next to it will be
a pool table.
그것 옆에는 당구대가
놓여질 것이고요.
Actually, we'll have
the logo on that wall too.
그리고 저쪽 벽에는 회사
로고도 들어가겠네요.
The logo, okay.
로고가 들어가는군요.
Yeah, and the logo
on that wall.
네, 로고가 저쪽 벽에
그려질 것입니다.
Cool.
그렇군요.
Over here is the Marcus'
and Jacobs' room.
여기는 Marcus와 Jacob의
방입니다.
They'll have their own
sound-proof room.
그들은 그들만의 방음처리된
방은 갖게 될 것입니다.
Pretty good.
꽤 좋네요.
Yeah, it's gonna
be great.
네, 정말 좋을 것 같아요.
It's really hard to,
really get your head around...
모든 것을 다 이해 하고
요약 정리 한다는 것은...
...everything and summarize,
but, you know,
...쉬운 일이 아닌것 같아요.
하지만, 아시잖아요,
obviously it's been the most
amazing year of my life.
저에게 있어서는 올해가 당연히
제 인생에서 가장 놀라웠던 한 해 였습니다.
Just going from, you know,
sitting in a shitty apartment,
그러니까 그냥 아무것도 아닌
똥통같은 아파트에 살면서,
you know, working on things
that I hate and you know,
제가 하고 싶어하지도 않는
일을 하는 직장 다니면서,
absolutely seeing no
future for myself aside...
제 미래는 아주 불투명해
보였습니다.
...from the few fleeting
moments of glory that I had,
제가 가끔씩 온라인에 픽셀
아트워크를 올려서 잠깐씩
you know, posting
some pixel art online,
누리는 영광의 순간들을
제외하고는 말이죠.
you know, going from that
to actually, you know, this,
그런 상황에서 지금의 상황에
이르기 까지, 그러니까...
travelling around the world
meeting fans and stuff like that,
전세계 방방 곡곡 돌아다니며
팬들을 만나고 하는 상황 말이에요,
it's been a pretty
wild ride.
굉장히 신나는 여행이었습니다.
A lot of things
happened last year.
작년에는 정말 많은
일들이 일어났습니다.
We recently changed
Minecraft's front page,
최근에 우리는 마인크래프트
웹사이트를 개편했습니다.
so it has my Twitter
account instead of Notch's,
이제는 제 트위터 계정 정보가 Notch의
트위터 계정 정보 대신 들어가 있습니다.
so... one difference.
그것이, 가장 큰 변화 중 하나 입니다.
So yeah, slightly before Minecraft
I asked Jens to take over...
네 그랬어요, 마인크래프트가 공개되기 직전에
Jens에게 제 자리를 물려 받아서...
...as the new game developer,
the lead developer of Minecraft...
...새 게임 개발자이자, 마인크래프트의
개발 총 책임자가 되어 달라고 하고...
...and I left the game
and now Jens is doing it.
저는 게임에서 손을 떼었고 현재는
Jens가 개발을 진행하고 있습니다.
We, we sat down and made
a plan in the beginning...
작년 초에 우리 모두 앉아서
계획을 짜 보았는데...
...of last year and that is still,
we still use the same plan...
...아직도 그 계획을 그대로
사용하고 있는데...
...because we only got
half ways through that list.
...그 이유는 아직 반 정도
밖에 완료하지 못했기 때문입니다.
I mean, I think we should be
able to do this in half a year,
제 생각에는 반년이면 이것들을
충분히 할 수 있습니다.
which means we won't, but at least
that's kind of a base "guesstimate."
그 말은 곧 못할것이라는 이야기 이지만
반년 정도는 기본 예상치로 잡아도 될것 같아요.
I barely talk to him
at all about Minecraft.
저는 마인크래프트에 대해서는
그와 거의 얘기하지 않습니다.
Sometimes I ask him small things,
but he said he didn't want...
그래도 가끔 사소한 것들에 대해서
물어보기라도 하는데, 그럴때면 자신은
...to interfere and he
has definitely not.
...간섭하고 싶지 않다고 말하고요,
실제로도 간섭하지 않습니다.
Well it's a relief and kind of a curse
'cause I won't ever be able to top that.
한편으로는 안심이 되기도 하고요, 어떻게 보면
저주에 걸린것 같아요. 왜냐하면 제가 더이상 발전시키지는 못하니까요.
It's a bit of a relief not to work
on something that big...
하지만 그렇게 큰 프로젝트에서 손을 떼어
약간이나마 부담을 덜 수 있게 되었습니다.
...because I think I've done
a lot of soul searching that...
덕분에 앞으로 무엇을 할지
더 많이 생각을 하게 되었고,
...that I'd rather work
on something smaller like--
조금 작은 무엇인가를 만드는
편이 낫겠다고 생각이 들었습니다.
'Cause I made Minecraft
kind of for myself...
왜냐하면 마인크래프트도 제 자신을
위해서 만들기 시작 했고,
...and that's the kind
of games I want to make,
오히려 그런 게임들이 제가
만들고 싶은 게임 같아요.
but now there are so many like kids
playing it and parents playing it...
하지만 지금은 너무나 많은 아이들과
학부형들이 즐기고 있고...
...and I can't really
understand that audience.
...저는 솔직히 그두 계층의
플레이어들의 입장을 잘 이해 못하고 있거든요.
So, it feels like there's a huge
responsibility to keep like...
그래서 굉장히 많은 책임감과 부담을
느끼게 되었습니다. 예를 들어...
...your child safe and make sure
the parents can actually use it...
...아이들에게 즐기기에 적합한 게임인지
학부형들도 아이들과 즐기고 싶은 대로...
...the way they want to use it
with their kids and stuff.
...즐길 수 있도록 되어있는지등
고려할 것이 많이 있었습니다.
So, I'd rather actually work on something
where I kind of understand the audience more.
그래서 제가 더 이해할 수 있는 계층을
위한 게임을 만드는 것이 더 낫다고 생각합니다.
So, after Minecraft came out,
the launch was a huge success,
그래서 마인크래프트가 나오고
런칭이 크고 성공적으로 마친 후에
and then he handed the development
off to one of his colleagues.
그는 개발에 총 책임직을 동료에게
넘겨주게 되었습니다.
I began to hear whispers of,
"Oh, he's just counting his money now,"
그런데 저는 이런 소문들을 들었습니다.
"그는 이제 편히 돈이나 세고 있나보군"
or, "He's not really that into
making games anymore."
아니면 "그는 이제 더이상 게임 만드는
것에 흥미가 없는것 같아."
And this struck me as strange
because it didn't really seem to fit...
그런데 이런 소문들이 제게는 이상하게
들렸고 제가 알고 있는...
...with the guy I had met a couple of times
and interact with over email or what have you,
몇번 만나고 이메일 상으로 서신을 주고 받은
그 사람과는 거리가 멀게 느껴졌습니다.
and he seemed to me like somebody
who's like, he loved doing this kind of thing.
제가 보기에는 그 사람은, 자신이 좋아서
게임을 만들고 즐겼던 그런 사람 같았거든요.
And it was, it was comforting and it was exciting
to find out that those whispers were wrong...
그래서 그 소문들이 거짓임이 들어났을
때는 정말 신나고 안심이 되었습니다.
...when his next game, which I'm still not even
sure how to pronounce, was announced...
그의 다음 게임은 아직 제가 어떻게 발음해야 할지
조차 모르는데, 그 게임이 발표 된 후에...
...and to find out very quickly thereafter
that it is potentially as insane as...
...이 게임도 마인크래프트 만큼이나
개념이 미치도록 신선한 잠재력이 있다는 것이...
...Minecraft was conceptually.
...확인 되면서 소문은
거짓으로 드러났습니다.
Yeah, I kind of burnt out
towards the end of Minecraft,
네, 마인크래프트 막바지에
좀 지치기는 했습니다.
just the pressure of releasing it and like
I realized that I was gonna move on,
릴리스를 해야 한다는 부담감 뿐만 아니라
저는 이제 이 일을 뒤로 남겨두고 더 나가야 한다는 생각,
and all that, and then I started getting
really inspired to make games,
그런 생각들 때문에 지쳤었는데, 갑자기
게임을 만들기 위한 영감들이 생겨서,
started doing the space game and
it feels like the beginning of Minecraft.
공간을 이용한 게임을 만들기 시작했는데,
지금 마치 마인크래프트 초기때와 비슷한 느낌입니다.
It's kind of just--you don't really know
what the game is gonna be.
그러니까 사실은 어떤게임이 될 것인지
잘 모르는 그런 느낌입니다.
It's like--it's scary because it could be something
completely different than what you thought...
약간 무섭기도 한 것이, 원래 생각했던 것 과는
완전히 다른 것으로 완성 될 수 있어서...
...and might not be fun at all,
it might be super fun.
...전혀 재미가 없을 수도 있고,
기똥차게 재미 있을 수도 있거든요.
So, it's very inspiring.
그런것이 제게는 영감을 줍니다.
I'm pretty sure Bethesda doesn't
have a trademark called "Ten to the C."
Bethesda는 10의 c제곱이라는 상표권은
등록하지 않은 것이 거의 확실합니다.
Damn it, I pronounced it!
이런 젠장, 발음해 버렸네!!!
Damn it!
젠장!
젠장!!!
I think I could put this up now
if I wanted to, but it's not really fun yet.
이제 공개하고 싶으면 할 수 있는
수준이지만 아직은 재미가 없습니다.
So, once it's kind of at the point where I can--
I would get lost for an hour instead of developing,
어느 시점엔가 제가 개발을 중단하고, 게임에
몇 시간씩 열중하게 된다면요,
then that's probably when
I'm going to release it.
아마도 그때가 제가
공개를 할 시기일 겁니다.
I guess I'm kind of afraid of the fans
being disappointed with the new game.
팬들이 제 새로운 게임에 실망할까봐
겁을 먹은 것 같습니다.
I mean it's a space game, it's not like a fantasy,
chopping game or whatever.
생각해 보세요, 공간 게임이에요, 환타지게임이나
뭔가 부숴버리는 그런 게임이 아니에요.
What the first big chance of success and the
chance of expectation is that when you're...
동네에 새로 이사온 아이라면,
성공에 대한 확률과 사람들의 기대치는...
...the new kid on the block, no one has formed
any expectations from you whatsoever,
...아무도 그 아이에게 그 어떤 종류의
기대감을 형성하지 않게 되지만,
and then when you exceeded, way,
exceeded people's expectations,
만약 사람들의 기대를 한번 뛰어
넘었더라면, 아주 크게 뛰어 넘었다면
asking someone to do
that again is really tough.
그럴만한 일을 다시 하라고 하는
것은 매우 어려운 일일 것입니다.
Usually what happens in a successful
situation is that the person, you know,
성공적인 상황에서 사람들에게
주로 일어나는 일들은 뻔합니다.
the sophomore slump kind
of thing, or like blows it all.
슬럼프에 빠진다거나,
실수를 해서 모든것을 날려버리죠.
I mean, if this was music, they'd blow it on crack
and hookers but, you know, I don't think--
만약 음악하는 사람이라면, 마약이나 매춘으로
일을 그르치겠지만, 저는 그가 설마--
And he's getting married and like he
doesn't seem like that kind of guy,
어쨌든, 그는 곧 결혼도 할 것이고,
그럴만한 사람이라고 생각하지 않습니다.
but at the same time, like stay focused on the thing
that you're trying to do and don't worry about,
그냥 한가지 일에 집중하고 다른 일들에
대해서는 많이 걱정하지 않았으면 좋겠습니다.
what I call, weather, right, like when you just can't,
you know, you can't control--it's gonna storm,
그러니까 날씨 같은 것은 어쩔 수 없는 문제니까요,
그렇잖아요, 폭풍이 올 수도 있는 것이고,
it's not, you know, whatever,
lightning's gonna strike, sometimes it doesn't.
우리는 어떤 벼락이 언제 칠치는
알 수 없는 노릇이잖아요.
You know, do all the variables you can control
and that's the quality of the game.
그러니 우리가 알고 있는 변수들을 제어하면
그것이 곧 게임의 퀄리티가 됩니다.
I've often felt creatively, it's key to have
a really bad memory and to forget what...
저는 간혹 창의적으로 느껴지는 경우가 있는데,
나쁜 기억력을 가지고 있어서...
...you did last and really start off each project
like it's your first one in a way,
...무엇을 마지막으로 했는지 잊고 새 프로젝트를
새로운 방법으로 다시 시작하는 것이 중요하다고 생각합니다.
and I feel like the trick is to do that almost
every time, just like go back to the beginning...
그렇게 하는것이 초심으로 돌아가는
일종의 트릭 같은 것이 되어서...
...and really treat each project like your
first project and start from scratch again...
모든 프로젝트를 첫 프로젝트를 백지에서
다시 시작하는 것 처럼 대할 수 있게되고...
...and not worry too much about people
are expecting or want from you,
...사람들이 자신에게 무엇을 바라는지
크게 걱정하지 않을 수 있게되어서,
but go back to the same place that gave you
your first idea, you know, you didn't get your...
아이디어를 처음 얻은 그 자리로 돌아갈 수 있습니다.
당신으로부터 나온 아이디어들은...
...first idea by listening to some advice from
a publisher or, you know, you just kind of,
게임 배포사나 그런 다른 곳에서
오는 것은 아니잖아요,
you followed what you love and cared about
and followed what really inspired you and that's...
당신이 무엇을 사랑하고 소중하게 여기는지에 따라
거기서 진심으로 얻는 영감들을 통해서...
...where your idea came from and that's
what you should do every time.
...아이디어들이 오는 것인데, 그런 식으로
매번 아이디어를 얻어서 시작해야 합니다.
Great, sorry about
the coughing.
수고하셨습니다. 그런데
기침해서 죄송합니다.
No, it's fine.
아닙니다, 괜찮습니다.
I'm sorry that, uh...
제가 미안하죠, 어...
I had a cold and then I talked too much
and don't breathe enough and that's what happens.
감기가 걸렸는데 말을 많이 하다보니까
숨을 충분히 못 쉬게 되어서 그렇게 되더라고요.
We should probably try to wrap up
before we get stampeded.
아마도 사람들 우루루 몰려오기 전에
우리는 여기서 마무리 짓는 것이 좋겠네요.
Okay.
그러시죠.
Okay, yeah, I think
we'll have lots of time.
네, 그래요, 제 생각에는
시간이 많을 것 같아요.
I don't think so, I mean,
I'll talk forever, so like--
안그럴걸요, 제 말은
제가 말이 많아서, 그러니까...
You gotta start
with something.
그래도 어떤 주제를 갖고
시작하셔야 할것 같습니다.
I'd still like you to
show us the game.
만드신 게임도 저희들에게
보여주셨으면 좋겠습니다.
You guys should play.
꼭 해보시는 것이 좋을것 같습니다.
All set?
다 되었나요?
That's a
clapper board is it?
지금 하신 것이
클래퍼 보드 대용인가요?
Yeah.
네.
Wow.
와우
Awesome.
멋졌습니다.
I wasn't even hot,
like it didn't even--
저는 하나도 덥지 않았습니다.
그러니까 그것이--
Shut up.
닥치세요.
I'm burning up.
저는 불타고 있습니다.
I mean it's not like we were
moving around or anything.
제 말은 우리가 막 움직이면서
무엇을 하고 그랬던 것은 아니잖아요.
I was packed between
you two guys.
저는 당신들 사이에
낑겨있었잖아요.
Minecraft--wait, it's an M.
마인크래프트~ 잠깐만, 'M'이어야 하는군요.
Minecraft.
마인크래프트~
Feel free to use that
as your logo for your movie.
제가 방금 한것을 당신들 영화의
로고로 마음껏 사용하셔도 됩니다.
Minecraft--what are
you calling it anyway?
마인크래프트~ 근데 영화
제목을 무엇으로 지을 건가요?
What, the movie?
영화 말입니까?
Yeah.
네.
Minecraft.
마인크래프트요.
Where do you
get your ideas?
도대체 그런 아이디어는
어디서 나오는건가요?